and fulfillment of every dimension of our personhood.
His resurrection shows that we cannot become truly human apart from him,
for only he has conquered the fear of death, that is at the root of our misery and corruption.
We must unite ourselves to him in joyful obedience, such that his life becomes ours,
even as we remain flesh and blood in this world.
Then we will say with St. Paul, it is no longer I who live, but Christ lives in me,
in me.
and the life which I now live in the flesh I live by faith in the Son of God who loved me and gave Himself for me.
The season of Palska has only just begun.
Because of our Lord's bodily resurrection, we must become holy in our bodies and treat our suffering neighbors accordingly.
Let us continue to celebrate by participating as fully as possible in the joy of the empty tomb.
For now nothing, absolutely nothing other than our own...
and stupper and refusal can hold us back from becoming truly human for Christ is risen.
Indeed he is risen.
The name of the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit won, God.
Amen.
You have been listening to Eastern Christian insights with Father Philip Lamasters, homilies
from St. Luke Orthodox Church in Abilene, Texas.
This has been a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
Glory to Jesus Christ, glory forever,
you're listening to ancient faithradio.com.
He will be a staff for the righteous,
with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations,
and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate
with song the Lord of Spirits.
First in all, chapter 48, verses four through five.
The modern world doesn't take-
knowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
post this live call
focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Christ is risen. He truly is risen.
Good evening, Giants Killers and Dragon Slayers.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Emmaus Pennsylvania
and my co-host, Father Stephen D. Young,
is with me from Lafayette Louisiana.
And if you are listening to us live,
you can call in at 855 AF radio.
That's 855-237-2346.
And Mattress Kachruti is taking your calls tonight,
and we're gonna get to those in the second part of our show.
So what happens when we die?
It's one of the most frequently asked questions,
not just by Christians, but by pretty much everyone.
The idea that the human person simply sort of
winks out of existence at the moment of death
is kind of on...
thinkable. The answer to this question is actually pretty clear within the Orthodox Christian
tradition as expressed in the Holy Scriptures and elsewhere, yet nonetheless confusion remains.
And you can hear people say all kinds of stuff about it. Probably the most common thing that
people say about the soul after death is the idea that we either go to heaven or hell and that's
kind of it so father Stephen is there any merit to that model?
No.
None at all.
Right.
Yeah.
So yeah, tonight we're going to answer the musical question,
where do bad folks go when they die?
They don't go to heaven where the angels fly.
They go to a lake of fire and fry.
And you see the port of July.
Nice.
But that's not the whole answer.
So stay tuned for the rest of the show.
I didn't see a whole problem.
Right.
Um.
So yeah, we're going to as has been our want lately, because we tend to sort of touch
on things on this show.
We take one trajectory through a topic and then later on we come through from another
trajectory.
Yeah, another angle.
Yeah.
And so we've already talked about some of the things we're going to talk about tonight from
another angle.
when we talked about the underworld,
gave sort of the gizeteer to the underworld many moons ago.
It seems like it was a time ago.
About a year actually, or yeah, right?
It was about a year?
Yeah, I don't know. We're on COVID time.
So it's like dog years.
But,
so we have to start sort of by talking about
about the state of affairs.
before Christ, if we're going to talk about what happens when people die.
Yeah. So this is, I guess, our first half is what used to happen to people when they died.
Right.
Both what did they think was going to happen and then what did happen and how that was understood.
And so we have to go back and do a little bit of review. We're not going to do too much.
Yeah.
for us that could still be an hour's worth, but we're not going to do an hour's worth.
A little review of the whole concept of shill or haisies or the grave or the underworld,
as it was understood by ancient, their eastern civilizations, sort of including Israel and the Greeks.
bad. Although I am going to throw in a little bit of Norse because I can't help myself.
Yes.
as is your want.
So, yeah, and so it folks remember when we talked about
shiol in the way the grave, the realm of moat, we got a death.
The way that was talked about the ancient Near East,
shiol was pretty much a horror show, right?
It's pretty much a slasher movie.
Everybody down there is bad.
There's lots of demons down there.
It's not that the demons are like in charge of you and they're your work supervisors that they're poking you with the Chorks.
It's more like you get tossed in with the wild animals and wild animals do what they do.
It's funny to me that image of the underworld is kind of like, you know, industrial revolution underworld where the demons are in charge of stuff.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, melodic.
Yeah, right. But yeah,
a manual labor that you
said, yeah, exactly.
You're often expected to work.
Yeah, you're segue, you segue
then to see us Lewis,
the cubicle part of hell.
But yeah, so the refereeing who we've
talked about, who are giants, their
spirits are the underworld.
They get talked about as being in
the underworld by I say, yeah,
some of the salt, including a salt,
we're going to talk more about later.
And we have a whole ritual in Ugaritac
that was performed at Ugarit when the king died.
Oh yeah, yeah.
The whole goal of the sacrifices that were offered and everything was to try to get him safely past the referee.
safely passed his ancestors.
We're going to shred him
as he was trying to get to the underworld.
So yeah.
Yeah, it's bad stuff.
Insert, you know,
Hellraiser one or two, three with Silly.
It was after that even though I'd apply in Sandrix,
and not worth watching, but one or two.
So this is sort of the Semitic version, right?
So not only Israel, but also other Semitic cultures
nearby.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
And as we've said before, Greece is really, even though people tend to look at Greece as
the first sort of Western civilization, in reality, the sort of the last ancient Near Eastern
civilization, sort of all the ways that count, right?
All the traditions you find sort of grow out of ancient Near Eastern traditions that they
inherit from Babylon and Egypt and their neighbors.
So you get...
But hey, these, but hey, these is a little different.
As we've talked about before and that it's a little more emo.
Yeah, right.
I mean, you've got like you've got the,
I mean, the best you've got is the Elysian fields, right,
which is still pretty lame.
Yeah, it's just less lame.
Yeah, yeah, but most everybody down there is just sort of,
you know, gloomy and going to be forgotten.
Yeah, like that's that.
once they're forgotten, they're gone.
You do get some, I mean, this is where you get
some pretty clear sort of regions of Hades.
You've got Tardarus where the Titans are imprisoned.
You've got people like Cicifist pushing his rock
up the hill over and over again.
But it's not great.
I mean, the nicest that you get out of it
is really hatey's himself down there.
you know when he's got his captured bride to put it mildly that's about as nice as it gets
which is not great. Yeah right right. He's pretty mid-80s Robert Smith down there. Yeah he did
not he did not get the nice realm. Yeah so the whole the whole place is kind of like if anybody ever
went to the castle in Tampa, Florida in the late 90s.
Light.
Join.
division, level terraces apart again in heavy rotation, it's just kind of sad and depressing.
Do they play the cure? They play the cure a lot over the loudspeakers.
And when, even when you read someone goes and counters or wants to talk to one of the shades in 80s, like when you listen to someone's up and killing a shade, it's just like, here's some depressing poetry I wrote.
Right. Down here by myself.
Right.
So, bye.
sort of the key thing here is that that's where everybody goes. Yeah, there's no way around it.
It might be a slightly nicer or slightly more horrible part of it, but that's where everybody
goes when they die. There's no like, there's no idea that human life ends at death and this
This goes well back into prehistory.
We're at the burials we find that like go-
that we've talked about in the Neolithic era.
We find burials, so the burials have grave clothes
and great goods and stuff.
So it's very clear that they didn't think the existence
such as person was over.
Yeah, actually just last night I watched the Netflix film The Dig.
Have you seen that?
Oh, so it's about the Sutton Who excavation.
again.
in 1939, which is an Anglo-Saxon ship burial.
And there's really nice treasure in there,
which, again, to underline the point,
why would you put really nice treasure down with dead bodies
if you didn't think that did anything?
You know, like what a stupid thing to do.
Let's bury some of our best stuff down here,
unless you believed that there was an afterlife
that this person was connecting to a newer kind of.
for whatever your beliefs about that was,
where you're sending that along, you know,
either as a bribe for the ferryman,
or like you can use this stuff in the afterlife,
but in any event.
Yeah, oh, it's a good film actually.
I recommend it everybody.
Ralph Fines plays the lead character in that, so.
I think it's pronounced raf.
It probably is, but I, you know,
I don't speak it's a bit rich.
I don't speak it's which,
which is where he's from.
Yeah, so despite certain recent comments from his most recent book made by
Friend of the show Bart Irman. Everybody in the ancient world believed in an
afterlife of some sort of varying sorts. Usually not great, right? Right. The outside
like if you were the king or the emperor or something so you were basically
considered to be a God already.
you might get to go and hang out with the other gods.
Yeah, but that's not where most, I mean, that's one of the
like chance.
Yes, yeah, that's not most people, right?
It's good to be the king, but you know, everybody else, not so much.
Yeah.
And even that's not 100%.
Right.
I mean, the reason for the elaborate burials and rituals in Egypt was because it
was like a guaranteed thing that the Pharaoh would even make it.
Right.
Right even though he-
would seem to be divine. Yeah, well, since I got to bring up, you know,
Sutton who, which is a, you know, Anglo-Saxon burial, I'd like to give a little
note on the word hell for everybody. This doesn't count as etymology. This is
more of straight philology, actually. Yeah, so I don't have a jingle. I don't
have a philology jingle. So Chris, Hoel, if you're listening, I'm just throwing
that out there.
Yeah, so the word hell I sometimes this is my little
soapbox
About this you sometimes we'll get people that will say you know you have to say hey these you can't say hell these are not the same concept
and
the the problem with that
is that
There's that Christian tradition does not make a distinction between those two things
right that there's something called hell and there's something called Hades now if you
want to identify hell as being tardarus, then yes, I suppose you can say that hell is a region of
Hades. But within so hell is a Germanic word. And hell gets used in the earliest translations of
the Bible and other Christian literature into English to simply translate the word Hades.
That's just refers to the underworld and it has a pre-Christian usage as far as we know.
I mean all the letters
that we have about Germanic pagan religion is filtered through Christians. But it just means
the underworld and just like Hades and Sheol, it refers to not just the underworld but also the
God that controls it. Of course, the fun thing in Norse religion is that the God who controls the
underworld is actually a goddess. So I like to sometimes say that the devil is female in Norse religion.
And...
So, in terms of that basic sort of historical use of these terms,
Hell, Haiti's seal are essentially synonyms, right?
But as you said, there's different concepts within these cultures
of what the underworld is like.
So now within modern English, now a lot of people have this idea of hell
where you've got demons poking people in the butt and making them do hard labor,
like you said.
And so as a result, then a lot of people do prefer the word Hades because it's sort
of an underworld word that a lot of people...
don't know what meaning to fill that word up with. So I get that, right? I totally get that.
But at least in terms of saying, well, hell and hate is are two different things in Christian
theology. That's just simply not true. You might say that we've attached the word hell to a mistaken
understanding of it. But even then, as we go tonight, you're going to hear a lot more about
the underworld and before and after Christ and all that kind of stuff. But anyways, I just would
I would want to mention this so how does stroke and
sphethology
It's mentioned, for instance, the Grimna small, which is part of the poetic edda, and in that hell actually exists
beneath one of the three roots of igdrisseal the world tree.
So it's down there underneath the roots of a tree.
You know, people do go there and come back.
There's this notion that Balder will come back after having gone there after Ragnarok.
and it's not a great place to be.
This is the thing that they all have in common is that...
But you don't want to go there.
It's just not not great.
Even the good parts are not that great.
So there's our little note on the word hell.
Yes.
Yeah.
And I tend to emphasize the part you said there at the end that when people hear the word
hell now.
Yeah.
What they think of is not what an Anglo-Saxon product.
No.
Indeed no.
Right.
Exactly.
Yeah.
of this and that's why I for example people may have noticed prefer to use Hades or Shio just to
break that free because they call her hell but that's not her name. It's not her name. Yeah I'm
cool with all the terms but I'm you know I'm a constant endless teacher so I'm just like well
this is what it means in this context and but yes it's true I mean that's actually my preference
these days often as I refer to simply the underworld.
Which you have kind of like a CD Chicago gangster sort of thing.
Yeah, I was going to say it's fine.
The shadow knows what you're going to get to the heart.
That's right.
Yeah.
That's all that's so.
So with all of this, you know, or show slash
moody atmospheric theatricality, depending on your your
for the underworld.
We mentioned that this is pretty much what you get in the Old Testament too in terms of descriptions of she all the grave, right? The underworld.
It's both that it's not great that it's full of demons that you don't want to go there, but that everybody does.
but it's also important that within the Hebrew Bible,
there is a hope attached to that.
right? Uh, somewhat uniquely. Yeah. There is the idea that that that may not be just the end of the story. That may not just be the way of all flesh. Right.
Um, in a lot of ways, like the epic of Gilgamesh is this sort of epic struggle with that of Gilgamesh trying to find some way for Inca do and then himself not to die.
Yeah, right and the answer at the end
is there isn't one.
Right, even for our giant Nephilim friend Gilgamesh,
it's inevitable, right?
But it's not necessarily the case
in significant portions of the Old Testament.
And so there are lots of places we could go.
And I'm sure we will get comments on the episode,
like why didn't you talk about this passage?
So it's a news genre of comment that we get.
You talked for three hours and didn't mention this one thing
that's related.
It's true, we did.
Yes.
We have sympathy for our beautiful engineer
at a good faith in the studio that
want to keep her until midnight while we go through every single
possible.
But it's a book.
Oh, we're going to.
We're gonna focus on.
is a particular set of songs.
And I say set of songs, not because it's one
of the song collections.
So the book of songs itself,
whether we're talking about the Greek book of songs
or the Hebrew book of songs,
is a collection of songs obviously, right?
They're written by different people at different times, right?
Within the book of songs, there are five books
books that are collected
there and they're labeled in a lot of English Bibles. People don't pay much attention to it
because basically it's completely mysterious right? We have no idea when those five separate books
were each collected. When they were all collected together as the Book of Psalms as we have it now
Now we have no idea really what connects the various zones in the different collections.
There's lots of dissertations and journal articles written about it.
So it's kind of a constant mill for generating that kind of stuff for people who are interested
in human poetry.
But the fact that it keeps generating all that stuff is due to the fact that number one,
it's mysterious and number two, nobody really knows.
Right.
Because if anybody had figured it out, you know, you reach homeostasis in the journal book.
Which we can't have that.
Yeah, yeah.
So that one would come along and try to upset the apple cook.
But I just mixed a metaphors in a crazy way.
It's okay.
It's all right.
So these Psalms are a group of Psalms because they're all attributed to the same group of people.
Yeah.
And that group of people is identified as the sons of Korah.
And this is Sun's indecendence. Not Sun's indecendence.
first generation literal songs.
Right.
And so this was one of the clans within the Levites
that had a kind of dark history that we've talked about before on the show.
So this is another thing we're going to try and review at a somewhat shorter link.
Yeah. If you want the whole story, go to numbers chapter 16.
And you can read the whole Korra episode.
or whichever episode it was or we talked about it.
Yes, because I don't remember these things.
And but so what happened was Korra and his clan
attempted to seize the high priesthood
for for himself
Although he did it by making a very egalitarian sounding argument. Yeah, you know Moses. Why have you and Aaron?
Why are you lording it over us? You know are we all priests?
You know, yeah
and that went badly for him and most of his immediate
clan members.
The ground opened and swallowed them up.
And so, Kora went down alive into Hades.
And the now third hand joke that we told the last time was
that Kora pulled a reversal like that.
And then, the last time,
quote-unquote the reverse Elijah.
that had gone alive into heaven, he went alive into shi'ol.
But there were certain members of his family and his clan who had joined in the rebellion
who identified there in number 16, who survived.
And it is the descendants of those members of Korah's family in that clan who wrote these
these solves. And so these are solved.
written by Levites, so these are Psalms that were intended for some kind of worship context that we
don't know for sure. But there is within them, if you read them, a recurring theme of being rescued
from death, being rescued from shiol, being rescued from Hades if you're in the Greek.
And so these Psalms, the Hebrew numbers that you'll find in most English Bible.
are 42, 44 through 49, 84, 85, 87 and 88. And if you want the Greek numbers, subtract one
from each of those. Which is the general rule, but not perfect when you're comparing the
Greeks to the middle part of this all. All of these are the middle part of the solve.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, you could think, you know, like having seen the head of their
clan and a bunch of their relatives gets sucked
down into the underworld, that would be kind of on their mind.
It would be, you know, a tradition within the family, right?
So that's like we talked about, we talked about that idea of sort of personal
history, like experiential history.
Right. Yeah.
So there's still the sons of Korra.
Their clan still bears the name of this person.
Yeah. Right.
And, and so that's a reality for them.
This event is part of their...
personal history of the way that it was for, you know, a Benjamin.
Right.
Even though the Benjamin, obviously, would have heard that story in the Torah.
It was not in that personal sense, right?
They weren't carrying that name around.
So we chose, I remember how we did this.
We cast lots, something like that.
I don't know.
to take a closer look at Psalm 88 or 87.
Yeah, okay.
It's an example of this rather than trying to work through all of them.
Okay, so I'm going to read it and this, I'll just tell everybody, this is the translation
from Holy Transfiguration Monastery here in the US in Massachusetts, which is very, very
commonly used in a lot of Orthodox churches using English.
And this translation is from the Greek version.
And I'm going to read it once through and then we're going to comment on some specific
items as we go.
So it's Psalm 88 or 87 in the Greek numbering.
O Lord God of my salvation, by day of I cry and by night before thee,
Let my prayer come before thee, bow down line ear into my supplication.
For filled with evils is my soul and my life under Hades hath drawn nigh.
I am counted with them that go down into the pit.
I am become as a man without help free among the dead like the bodies of the slain sleep in the grave
whom their remembers no more, and they are cut off from thy hand.
They lead me in the lowest pit in darkness.
and in the shadow of death. Against me is that anger made strong and all I all I
billows has thou brought upon me. Thou hast removed my friends afar from me, they
have made me an abomination unto themselves. I have been delivered up and have not
come forth. My eyes are grown weak from poverty. I have cried unto the O Lord the
whole day long. I have stretched out my hands unto the
nae for the dead, wilt thou work wonders, or shall physicians raise them up
that they may give thanks unto thee. Naysha, and any in the grave, tell of thy
mercy and of thy truth in that destruction.
Nasha, thy wonders be known in that darkness,
and thy righteousness, and that land that has forgotten.
But as for me unto thee, O Lord, have I cried,
and in the morning shall my prayer come before thee,
wherefore, O Lord, to stow cast off my soul,
and turn as thy face away from me.
A poor man of mine and troubles for my youth,
ye having been exalted, I was humbled and brought to distress.
Thy theories have passed upon me,
and thy tears have sorely troubled me.
They came around about me like water,
all the day long, they compassed me about together.
Thou hast removed afar from me, friend and neighbor,
and minor queens is because of...
my misery. It's kind of a bummer of a song. There's no point at which it gets better.
Yeah, there's no happy. Yeah, yeah, yeah, of course. Yeah. It's the new battle,
Sargalactica. So, yeah, as people probably noticed on the way through, right,
they
the the solmest, whichever son of
Koura was who who wrote this is
reflecting the situation of someone
who is dead, right?
Someone who is in the pit,
someone who is in the 80s, right?
Like in the pit, in the grave, right?
The bodies of the slain sleep in the grave.
Yeah, I mean, this isn't just someone
saying I'm really bummed and it's like being,
it's like I'm in the grave.
I mean this is this...
This is from the point of view of someone as you said, who is there?
Yeah, sort of like Jonas Pair as we've talked about before.
But this is somebody who God has forgotten who's cut off from the hand of God and from
the life that comes from his hand, right, in the lowest pits, right?
And isolated, separated from everyone.
So there are a few places when we get to about them.
middle of the song where there are some things that are kind of hidden in the English translation.
Right. Right. One of those is we get a couple of sort of rhetorical questions.
Right, the first one being in this English translation, nae for the dead will that work wonders.
Right, or will that work wonders for the dead? Right. We put it more common.
I think it was phrasing, right?
And the dead there, right, is sort of the typical
work for the dead.
It's from the root moat, right?
It's just dead people, right, in the Hebrew.
But then in the English, because it's going through the Greek,
there's this phrase, or shall physicians raise them up
that they may give thanks unto thee.
Yeah.
Yeah, and so we look this up we checked we did a little word study because
What is in the Hebrew right? It's it doesn't say physicians. It says
The Refaim
Well the referee will the Refaim arise and praise thee. Yeah, it's not will
Something raise someone else up
In the Hebrew in the Hebrew it's will the Refaim rise up and praise the you know, in other words the dead giants, right?
So yeah, we look at the Greek version of this song and the word that's used there that they translate is Yatri, which means doctors physicians.
right? So, Physicians is a good translation from the Greek, right? But we puzzled for a moment or two,
and then you found the answer as to why whoever translated this...
this Greek text of the Psalm, why they would use the Greek word for doctor to translate
Refaim, right?
And you...
Yeah.
The mistook Refaim for Rofaim is basically the short version.
And Rofaim would mean healers, basically, as opposed to Refaim.
First of all, the...
make that misread, you have to add a letter that isn't there.
But then also, in order to translate it from the Greek into English and have it make sense,
they had to add a bunch of words.
Yeah, right.
Because the Greek is more literally something like, will physicians rise and give thanks
to me?
which if you got this picture the underworld, you know?
Right. It's like, oh, and oh, and here's doctors, which doesn't does it. Right. So it
in even in the Greek translation, it doesn't totally make sense. So, you know,
it took rise to change it to raise the top. Yeah.
They made it a transitive verb and added a pronoun, right, in order to make it make sense.
Right. Yeah. So I mean, and you know, this probably makes some people mad, but
It's well known there are a handful of mistakes in the Greek Old Testament.
Well, I'd like to have you to talk about which Greek.
Yeah, right. Exactly. There's several.
Yeah, there's a lot.
Yes, there's a lot of textual differences, right?
Yeah, and some of them seem to be based on some that they're looking at a Hebrew that's
different than the other Hebrew versions we have and others that they're, you can see
that they made a mistake. They've missed.
understood a word or just didn't know what the word meant and so they kind of guessed.
Right.
You know, because that's how we translation works.
Yes, and so let me be completely on the nose about it.
All of the Greek translations into English that you're reading are not translations of
V Greek as if there's the A V Greek stored somewhere.
They're translations of codex synaticus.
Yeah
So, the translations of A Greek manuscript of the Old Testament from the 4th century AD.
Right. So there's a lot of other Greek that's out there, Greek versions.
So, what we're really saying is that somewhere either when Codex that I addicus was being
or before that somebody made a poop.
Hmm.
And since Codex Sinaiaticus has at least three hands of corrections in the book, right?
Like, even the monks, Mount Sinai clearly thought there were mistakes in it, because they
kept correcting them.
Yeah.
So no one has ever said that it's a perfect manuscript.
But anyway, now we've made all those disclaimers that won't stop anyone from getting mad at us
anyway
the dead doctor is rising up in the underworld.
Hey, whatever.
So, but it refers to the referee, right?
But the idea here is obvious behind that question, right?
It's that, you know, you're not
praised in worship of God is not possible in shi'ol.
Right.
In radius.
And so, this verse is calling out to God, you know,
that he wants to give praise and worship to God.
right but needs to be set free in order to do that right and that's why I
immediately after those questions and here's the English translation we're
working with. They shall any in the grave tele-dimersi and upside-truth in
that destruction and the Hebrew of destruction there is Abadon which fans of
the book of Revelation might be familiar with remember Abadon or Apollion in
Break. Yeah.
destruction. And then toward the end, when it's translated in English, thy furies have
passed upon me and thy tears have sorely troubled me and they came or browned them about
me like water. These are those demon non-friends, right, in the underworld. Coming around like
water is not like, oh good, I have something to drink or finally a bath, right? This is
like flood waters, this is water is the course of chaos.
these demonic beings that are being called furies and terrors right here.
So all of this, even though this doesn't have, as some of the other Psalms, of course, have a
sort of Danumah where that rescue or salvation from death and Hades is being explicit,
it. Right? It's definitely pointing to it. It's crying out for it.
it's calling out for it, right, to Yahweh the God of Israel.
And the way that this text,
this particular text, Saul, 88 or 87,
ends up getting interpreted is in terms of Christ.
Yeah.
So you will see references to Christ being the one
who is free among the dead,
rant which is aligned from this song.
And one important part of the very early
proclamation of Christ resurrection
that we see in the early sermons in the book of Acts.
We get this quotation that's made of Psalm 16, verse 10,
which is not a Psalm of the sons of Korah,
but it's a Psalm of David.
But what is you'll not abandon my soul to shayol
or let your...
Holy One's decarruption. Right. And it's pointed out, I tell you to this day, David remains
in his tomb, right? So yeah, this isn't a reference to David.
Right. This is a reference to Christ. But, but it was not seen as being limited to Christ.
Right, there's not seen as being limited to Christ.
So Christ's resurrection.
was he was being linked to the resurrection minimally of all human beings.
He's the first fruits from the dead.
That language is used.
And I want to pause on this for a moment because one of the sort of bugaboo's out there,
of course, is that, you know, as soon as Christ's resurrection happens,
We load up all the Judaism, throw it in the dumpster, and start over and make a new religion, right?
And then things just sort of evolve, but then at a certain point all this Greek philosophy shows up and gets shoved into Christianity somewhere and everything ends up weird.
Okay.
But if right here, based on souls, based on Hebrew poetry, we have the idea, the apostles receive the idea as they express it.
these early sermons, that.
Christ's salvation from hate
affects all of humanity
right, liberates all of humanity in some sense from death and from hate
right?
That means that they have some sense of the solidarity of Christ and the rest of humanity
hmm
used as it were. Yes. What Christ does
And what Christ is and what happens to Christ, right, is, is effectual for all of humanity.
So you get an idea in Greek, used to express that solidarity like Homoesias, or saying
that Christ took about himself our human nature, which he shares with us.
Those are Greek terms.
are not, e-reuters that are not especially biblical terms, right?
But they're used to explain things, right, in Greek,
because people spoke Greek at the time,
to explain in Greek concepts.
They're already there, again, going all the way back
into this Hebrew poetry from centuries before Christ, right?
And on top of that, now that we've got Christ
being homo-usials with us, because he shares our human nature,
They also take these traditions and weld them into
traditions that we talked about in a past episode about Yahweh, the God of Israel, invading
Hades.
Remember, lift up your heads, oh, ye gates.
Right.
Right?
To rescue people and they meld them together, which means what?
Which means Christ is Yahweh, the God of Israel and Christ shares our human nature.
Right.
So the incarnation is literally built into the Old Testament and, you know, very clear
Christology. It's not just some later...
reflection like, oh, he must have been God. You know, right?
Or yeah.
Yeah.
But the question comes, how do we explain this and make it clear in Greek?
Because that's the way you're making it.
It's amazing.
Greek vocabulary drawn, just like we do this show in English.
Yeah.
Technically, no English word that we've spoken during this podcast ever
appears in the Bible because the Bible was not written in English.
Wait.
What?
Sorry, he James only posted.
Oh man.
Right.
So there are no biblical English words.
Look, it got into English as quick as it could, okay?
We have to do our best to reflect those things.
But we're trying to use words in another language to reflect realities that are being conveyed
through the source language.
And
So we jumped ahead a little, right, talked about Christ in fulfillment, but we're going
to slide back a little again now, right.
So we see this idea and people can go on their own and read the other Psalms of the sons
of the Quaranton and see those similar themes and ideas playing out, right.
So we have this tradition.
With this tradition, as we see it reflected in the Psalms, for example, in the Hebrew Bible,
is not sort of completely articulated and developed.
Yeah
Right. It doesn't say, you know, in Psalm 88, 87 here, it doesn't say, and I know that the
time will come when your Messiah will arrive. Right. That's right. That's right. Right.
There's a sort of hope, right, and this prayer that's extended. Right. But that's not to
say that it just sort of stayed vague and nebulous until the time of the apostles of the writing
of the New Testament.
Yeah.
There's commentary on this, there's reflection on it,
there's other takes within various kinds of literature.
You know, as we do, right?
As we do, we don't just say, oh, we've got this text.
I mean, even the most solar-scriptural Protestant
says things about the Bible
and comes up with ways of understanding it.
So of course that's gonna happen
in the ancient world as well.
Right, compares what one part says to what another part says.
Right.
how they work together, right? Right. Right. We all do that. They did that in the ancient world,
too. And so what example of sort of a greater articulation of this from before the time of Christ?
We're going to go back to the book of Enix Four Caves, right? And revisit this kind of quickly.
We already talked about this in our sort of geography of the underworld episode a little bit, too.
But this gives a good idea from the third century BC. So we're at least a couple hundred probably
more like 250 years.
for the birth of Christ, how they saw it.
So when Enoch is going on sort of his grand tour day cosmos
and seeing everything,
he sees in Hades these four caves
with four groups of people living in that.
And so the first group is the righteous.
second group is the wicked.
You probably predicted those two, right?
Um, the good, the bad, the ugly, wait.
No.
Well, no, we can't really make that work.
Okay, sorry.
So you've got the right just in the wicked.
Then the martyrs.
Yeah.
And the martyrs are sort of led by Abel.
Enixie's Abel, like kind of outside the cave,
crying out to God.
Uh, for justice.
that that passage is.
very parallel. We don't have it in Greek, so we can't tell exactly how parallel, but very
well parallel to the souls of the martyrs crying out for justice in St. John's. But so able
is there sort of represent use the first one, right? And then the fourth group is the ignorant,
right? So this is like mostly Gentiles, right? Who didn't know any better, right?
ever heard.
Yeah, yeah. And so each of these groups has their own cave. They're all in Hades though.
But the the righteous and the martyrs have access to this spring of water.
Yeah, and as a sort of echo of that, of course, is a reference really almost this shows up in
in the Gospels, where you've got the parable of the rich man in Lazarus, where the
Richmond is burning and he says to Abraham, you know, send Lazarus over because you've got water access over there.
Can you please send me some, send me some water?
And I know when I called it the parable of the Richmond and Lazarus,
there's probably a couple of people that are like, oh, wait, that's not a parable.
And just for fun, I decided to look, to at least look up one patristic reference to this.
and so I pulled the trusty old St. Theaful active
Oakrid off of my shelf who has these wonderful commentaries on the Gospels and some other
texts from the New Testament and he's rightly called sort of the Clip Notes version of
St. John Chrysostom.
He almost always just follows whatever Chrysostom says and just restates it in brief.
And he very explicitly calls it a parable in his commentary on that and calls it a story
and so forth.
So it's okay people.
It is a parable.
the fact that it doesn't say it's...
beginning the Lord spoke this parable doesn't mean it's not. And we shouldn't take it, you know,
when we look at it, we shouldn't say this is what the underworld is like exactly. You know,
this is an image that Christ is using to tell us something.
And if you read it in Greek, it actually begins the exact same way as the parable of the good
Samaritan.
Hmm.
Pamela Goods-Samaritan starts out, you know.
a certain man, some guy, going down to Jericho,
and the Parable Rich Manilizer
starts out a certain rich man
beasted sumptuously every day.
Yeah. Right. Right.
So it's just, it's the typical beginning of a parable.
Right. That should be controversial
for people. Once upon a time,
it's like that whole different verbs were love thing.
Yes, I brought it up again.
So, so please
These four groups, Enoch is told, have four different destinies.
They're still at this point when Enoch sees them.
They're still all in Hades.
But Hades isn't the end of the line for many of them.
And so what he's told is that the righteous are going to go to paradise.
And Enoch later sees paradise and it's empty at that point.
So the righteous are going to go to paradise.
The Wicked are going to be thrown into the abyss, right, or Tartarus with the angels who
send the watchers, right, at some point in the future.
So they're not going to get to stay in 80s.
They're going to go somewhere worse, right?
Or I just are going to go somewhere better.
The martyrs are going to be taken into the heavens with God.
They're going to basically join the Divine Council, right?
sort of the reward for.
their martyrdom and the ignorant are just going to stay. So the book of Enoch, unless
your Ethiopian is not in the Bible. And this is not like the teaching of the Orthodox
Church that there are these four caves and that there are these four different destinates,
right? Right. We're just saying this is the understanding that's represented in this
take.
right before the New Testament comes right right and the reality comes in Christ
right this is sort of how people were thinking about it this is how the Jewish
people in Christ's day worth thinking about right and so you can even see where
some bits of this end up in certain like for example in Western Christian
traditions. There are these limbo
that are sort of never fully official,
but are always kind of around.
And you could see how like jumping ahead to Dante,
why do you think that Virgil,
who was one of the ignorant pagans,
but virtuous might be in kind of a limbo,
rather than like a Tarnerous Abyss situation.
That's sort of a continuation of this kind of idea.
So these threads do kind of play out and later...
Christian texts, but this isn't authoritative. This is how it was, right before. But, but at the same
time, we do see that there is this idea that, and it's pretty explicit in Enic, that when the Messiah
comes. He's going to begin this shift. Right? So
the righteous being brought out of Hades and into paradise is something the Messiah is going to do.
Right? And the martyrs having their justice is something the Messiah is going to do. These are
things that the Messiah is going to do when he comes. And so this is, you can see right away where
the sort of harrowing of Hades tradition then comes from in terms of understanding crisis,
fulfilling this in terms of the right-
just being brought to paradise for meetings. Right? That fulfillment, that second exodus, that second
posca, remember posca means Passover. Right? This exodus. And so this gets one mistake,
shall we say, that people make, is that they look at and they say, for example, so okay, so
So, Enoch is expecting the Messiah to do this.
So he's thinking the Messiah is just going to come once.
Right?
Messiah is going to do all these, just show up, he's going to judge everybody, he's going
to do all this and then that's end of days, that's game over.
But not only is that not reflected in second enec, something very different is reflected.
The reason it's not reflected in the book of enec is that it's not really reflected in the
prophetic purpose that's in the Hebrew Bible, that's in the Christian Old Testament.
because all of those have what you could call a two-stage eschatology.
Both of them have it.
Yeah, in some sense the Messiah coming twice.
Right, so there's, and I think this is a really important concept that,
that biblically, and correct me if I'm getting this wrong,
biblically, you have essentially three ages.
You've got the first age which is the covenant, you know,
So the initial covenant, right?
with Abraham. I mean I guess you could call, I guess yeah okay, I guess you could call what happens before that another age or whatever but but within the kind of Messianic
Matrix so to speak right there's kind of three there's there's you know this initial covenant that's prior to the coming of the Messiah
with this hope
Then you've got the Messianic Age when he comes and releases people from...
and so forth. And then there's an age in the future, from our point of view, an age in the future
that is the life of the world to come, right? The sort of the final age. So there's just three stages.
And so two stages, eschatology meaning there's an initial big change that happens. And we now live after
that or in it. And then there's another big change that's going to happen, which is going to wrap
everything up. Right? Basically, yeah. Yeah. You have a couple two few ages in the past. But yeah,
okay. Okay. So yeah, the breakdown be that there's before the expulsion from paradise. Yes, right. Right.
Right. So when we're talking about an age like this, we're talking about
It's not just like an arbitrary time period.
It's sort of a status quo for the cosmos, right?
It's sort of a shape of reality of the cosmos,
and how it relates to God and God relates to it.
Yeah.
Right, so there's the age before,
the expulsion from paradise,
that sort of protological age.
Then there's from the expulsion from paradise to the flood.
And then,
minimally, there's from the flood to the coming of the Messiah.
the coming of the Messiah starts the Messianic age.
There's the Messianic age.
and then there is a file shift the end of days.
and then there's an age without end.
Right.
So there's some debate depending on what sect and school of Judaism were talking about
the second temple period, whether the covenant and Sinai inaugurated a new age or not.
And this is a rabbit trail.
We could spend the rest of the night on.
But that's not what we're here for tonight.
But that's just...
Interesting as this.
I will just drop this and refuse to elaborate.
Moses was not all that important
to a lot of Jews in the second temple period.
And we'll move on.
So.
All right.
If you weren't a Pharisee.
So...
But yes, so there's this idea that from the future, from the time that the book of
Enep is written, or that the Old Testament is written, right? The next age, right? Even if you think
Moses inaugurated a new age, right? The earliest parts of the Old Testament date back to the time of Moses, right?
So all of that's written. The next age is going to begin when the Messiah comes, but when the Messiah
he's gonna inaugurate the Messianic Age and that age
Messianic age is not an age without end.
Yeah.
It is the final age before the end.
And then when the end comes,
then there's that age without end.
So there's always this two stage, right?
And judgment is always associated with that last stage,
that final judgment is the end of days
before the age without end, right?
That's where justice is finally established.
in the world, there's a new heaven to the new earth, right,
that everything changes.
But this messianic age, and we've talked about this
in different Psalms, right, this is the age when the Messiah
rules in the midst of his enemies, or it's said to my Lord,
sit at my right hand till I make your image, your footstool.
Right, and we shouldn't confuse the end of days
with these latter times, right?
Because we often make reference to these
these latter days or these latter times, that's the age run now, that's the
messianic age, whereas the end of days is the end point of this and then what
comes after that. Right, so the reason they call, they say, these are the, the
apostles say, these are the last days, right, is because we're now in the final age
before the end. Right, right, there's, there's nothing else that needs to happen,
This HID is awesome.
important though for another question we get a question a lot where people ask like
Some variation of well, how are things different now that we have the Holy Spirit?
Yeah, or how are things different now that the demons have been unseated or how are things different now and
That's kind of hard to explain right because if you look at each age is having sort of
Separate laws of spiritual physics
Right. So we can't understand what Adam and Eve's life and existence was like in paradise.
Right. Right. And they couldn't understand what ours is like. And so we can't fully understand what things were like before Christ accomplished.
any more that they could fully understand what they were going to be like.
after the big difference of course is that we do have like we do have historical record
right and what we do know from the historical which is not the same thing as being there right
but what we do have from the historical record shows a world very very different from ours
very very different from ours right and and the people who are there on the overlap are like
the Apostles.
Right.
And so you can read it the pages of the New Testament, how they felt everything had changed.
Right. Like the universe had changed when Christ rose from the dead.
According to St. Peter and St. Paul. Yeah.
They should say a literal game changer. Like it changed the rules of how everything works.
Yes, the cosmos is now different because this happened. Right.
Right. So yeah, so there is this massive shift. And so.
When we see in the ancient church movements of kiliasum,
modern church, different pre-millennialist groups,
what they've done is they've taken that two-stage
eschatology from the Old Testament
and pushed it forward to today, right?
So they still have this idea that Christ
is still going to come two more times.
once to rule in the midst of his enemies for a thousand years, and then the end of days
after that.
Meaning, and this is why the fathers condemned Kiliasim so harshly, because they said,
if you do that, you're saying that Christ didn't accomplish through his death and resurrection
what Christianity says he accomplished, because you're saying the Messianic age hasn't started
yet.
You
So Christ then didn't accomplish anything.
The Holy Spirit hasn't been given, right?
That's how they took it in the ancient church with kilesum.
And kilesum and pre-bellalism are not identical.
I'm not saying they're identical.
There's all kinds of different,
there's 83 varieties of pre-bellalism,
dispensational and otherwise, right?
But there's a common mistake there
holding to essentially an old testament eschatology
in the new testament.
of not seeing that Christ already came once.
And so now the second and last,
is the one that's ahead of us.
So, as we said, right,
we're now living in the Messianic Age,
and awaiting this end of days.
the final judgment. And as we've talked about justice is everything being in the right place,
everything functioning properly. And so it's the final judgment, not because this is when the
verdict is read and there's no getting out of it. It's the final judgment because this is when
once and for all, the whole cosmos is going to be put in order. Right. It's going to be just.
And so at that time, there are going to be
the devil and demons. At that time, there are going to be humans who are unrepentantly
wicked. If the whole creation is reestablished in justice, when everything is turned right,
then what does that mean for them? Do they exist? What is outside of everything? Right?
So we're going to be talking about.
for the rest of the night.
Exactly.
But as one last note, again, not that I'm trying to take shots at Fred
to the show, Bart Irman.
But you will read a lot of New Testament scholarship saying that
the Apostles all thought Jesus was going to come back right away.
And then he didn't.
So then they had to come up with like theology and
and then church institutions and stuff.
Yeah.
This is a really common kind of way to say.
Yes.
And the problem with that is this idea of a messianic age
is so clear in the Old Testament.
It's so clear that at the beginning of the second century,
you already have kiliasks.
You already have people projecting out
a messianic age into the future.
25 years is not an age.
ages last thousands of years, right?
Right?
Like the flood to the time of great.
So the fact that they saw it as an age means that no, they didn't necessarily think it was going to happen in 20 or 25 years.
They thought, they thought and they thought that it could at any time.
because there's nothing else that has
to happen before Christ returned, right? It could happen at any time. That doesn't
mean they thought it would happen within 20, 25, 30, 40, 50, 100 years. Right. Right. Right.
Right. And every illusion to it in the old and new testaments and in the earliest church
fathers of the second century that we have, I'll talk about it being a long time.
Hmm, the beginning age.
Yep.
Alright, well,
Well, well
We're going to take a quick break and we'll be back with some of your calls.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
secret turning.
A collection of short stories by Stephen Signari.
Many people, Muslims, Orthodox Christians,
Westerners, Armenians gathered for the execution
of Alexander.
Alexander stood in the center.
The executioner flashed his sword
in front of Alexander's eyes to frighten him,
but the martyr remained unaffected.
I will not exchange the light for darkness.
He said,
I worship Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, the Trinity Consubstantial and undivided,
and He made the Son of the Cross. Alexander prayed, but He did not change his mind.
So Alexander the whirling dervish from Thessaloniki sacrificed his life for the love of Jesus Christ
In the city of Smirna, Asia Minor on May 26th, 17...
Now available in paperback, e-book, and audiobook at store.inchantfaith.com.
Hey welcome back. We're still down in the underworld and we've got a couple of
callers. I bet you didn't know they had phone service in the underworld but they
do. And you know remember that show that we did work?
This is where all the companies have their customer service. Oh you remember
that show we did where everybody was named Ben. Well we've got two callers both
named Michael. So we're going to take Michael number one, Michael number one, you're there.
Yes, can you hear me? Yes, we hear you welcome Michael to the Lord of
Spirits Christ is risen. Truly is risen. It's good to talk to
you again, fathers. And I had a question that I wanted to set up by
referring to the episode you did the bodies and the bodyless
and you set a prayer, a prayer for one who was suffered long and who
is at the point of death. And right right in the middle of that prayer
there was something that ever since I heard it was kind of a
a puzzler for me and it's that part that says that the
body, therefore, it dissolved from the elements of which it was fashioned, but that the soul
be translated to that place where it will remain until the general resurrection.
And so when I hear this general resurrection and I just heard the first half of your show,
I'm wondering, is the general resurrection that final judgment?
And does one experience the passage of time when they pass away like we do in this world,
like we do with Kronos time, or when we die, is it like Kyra's time?
the eternal time.
of God where the past, present, and future are all the same.
Yeah.
So, I mean, some of the answer to that is basically keep listening to this half of the show.
I mean, well, you know, we love it when we have a good layup, right?
But, I mean, just to give you a little bit of a, give you something to go home with,
one thing that I think is important to understand is that, and we didn't make this explicit
I don't know, correct me, Father, if I'm getting this wrong.
The scripture actually references two resurrections.
There's what's called the first resurrection, which is one
that involves the saints.
And of course, this begins with a harrowing of hateys,
where the souls of the righteous are resurrected.
And then there's the second resurrection, which
is the general resurrection of all of the dead,
where material bodies are going to be raised.
And so.
So part of what you're hurting that prayer is a reference to that second resurrection
that everyone's going to participate in, both the righteous and the wicked.
All will be raised no matter what.
And the reason why that's going to happen is because Christ has redeemed human nature
and since we all share in human nature, death is being defeated for all of us, no matter
what.
Which is not the same thing as being saved, right?
But we will all rise from the dead.
So that's part of what's going on there.
We're gonna talk a little bit about-
We're going to talk more about the soul and what happens with the soul at death.
So I'm just going to ask you to hang on and keep listening for that.
I don't know, Father, do I leave something out or something maybe corrected, whatever?
Well, just in terms of the idea of the first resurrection, the second resurrection, we've
talked before.
I know about how and every time I say this, I'm cribbing this from...
John of Damascus. There's a footnote for everybody. Nothing wrong with that. I mean,
see, John Damascus is pretty much the schoolmaster. There's two kinds of death, right? There's
spiritual death and there's physical death. Physical death is the separation of the soul from the body.
spiritual death is the separation of the soul from God. Who is the source of life? Right? So when we...
talk about souls being brought from Hades into the presence of God to Christ or from this
world to Christ for people who die now, modestly. That's called the first resurrection because
the soul coming to Christ, coming to God, is made alive. Is the resurrection of the soul.
There's the resurrection of, there's the spiritual resurrection.
direction of the person.
And we've talked before, also, I know about how we tend
to get those two kinds of death backwards.
We tend to think that the separation of the soul from the body,
that physical death is actual real death because it's material,
and real stuff is material stuff.
And then spiritual death is some kind of metaphor.
So we've got to wish you, actually, metaphor thing.
Because everything's going to be...
spiritual is wishy washy and oo-woo, right.
But from the perspective of Scripture, the fathers, and teaching the Orthodox Church, it's
exactly the opposite of that.
Spiritual death is real death, right?
Because as Christ says, this is life to know you, the only true God in Jesus Christ, whom
you have set.
That's what it means to be alive.
So that's real death.
And physical death is sort of...
of an analogy or an image of what that real death is.
So, the reason why, for example, Revelation 20, where that first resurrection language
is used for the souls of the parted, say, John says,
blessed are those who have a part in the first resurrection.
to be envied. These are right.
is because
experiencing the real resurrection already.
And the physical resurrection is just sort of that playing out.
In the same way that when Adam and Eve
part took in the fruit of the tree of knowledge of good and evil,
they spiritually died immediately.
They separated themselves from God.
And then that played out over time until they died.
the same way now it's reversed, that spiritual death, that spiritual resurrection happens first, and then the bodily resurrection plays out on the last day.
So there you go, Michael. Does that make sense?
It does. Thank you, Father's both very much. I'm looking forward to hearing the rest of the show. Great show.
Awesome. Thank you very much for coming. Okay. We've got another Michael on the line. So Michael, are you there? Christ is risen.
truly is risen.
Welcome. What's on your mind, Michael?
Yeah, so I had a question. Um, well, before I asked my question, I just wanted to extend a
thanks to a UN Father Steven podcast, like this one, Full Council of God. They've been very helpful
for, um, myself, my family, my friends in coming into the church. So I just wanted to say thank
you for that before I asked my question. Thank God. Thank God. So my question is, um,
It's regarding this.
a point that was made in your April 15th episode,
how to and how to not read the Bible.
Okay.
Yeah, there was a point,
I think it was towards the end of the first half
where it was mentioned that the Bible
doesn't make scientific or historical claims.
And my question regarding this is the accounts
of the resurrection, like the bodily resurrection
and the gospels and the epistles.
I've always understood.
was to mean that the resurrection physically happened.
It wasn't just a metaphorical idea or a theory or an idea
or an abstract concept.
Like it was a thing that happened physically
and in every part of reality.
Like Christ fills up all realities.
And so I was just wondering, is the gospels and the epistles?
Are they not making a historic
with regard to the resurrection and any other claim that they make for events that actually happen in history.
I was just hoping you could expand on this.
Okay. So, okay. Well, Father Steve, I'm just going to push that over to you because this is a point that you were especially trying to make in a very fine precise way about the Bible and historical claims.
Right, yeah. And the issue is with that language of making claims. Right?
So the question is, right, when someone makes a statement, any statement, they're making
that statement within a certain set of beliefs and values and understandings of the world,
right?
conditions and sort of explains that statement.
And so if you have someone, then say centuries and centuries later, in a different context
in a different culture and a different language, right, and they try to evaluate that statement.
Just take that exact statement from the ancient times and they want to evaluate it.
You can't evaluate it within, you're now modern, pre-suppositions and understandings and
for this sort of thing, right?
So, for example, if in the context that I'm using the term like scientific claim, if you're
going to say that the accounts of Christ resurrection were making a scientific claim, you would
mean that in terms of modern science, right, that you were making a claim as to how the
the resuscitation of Jesus' physical body took place.
Right.
That you're making a claim to well, right?
And you say, well, that would be ridiculous, right?
And that's not what people mean.
Right.
But I would point you to our friend Ken Ham, right?
Who does make those kinds of strange scientific arguments?
Right.
so like well before the
flood, there was a firmament and so that raised the barometric pressure and that would make snakes not venomous.
That's an argument he makes, right? He's saying, well, okay look, the Bible is making these claims,
scientific claims. So he tries to use modern science to make them justifiable claims because
because he's treating them as modern science and the clubs.
But they're not modern scientific.
because the people who wrote them weren't sort of breathing the atmosphere of modern science, right?
It wasn't how they thought about things that wasn't what they were trying to convey. And so I met
the same thing in terms of historical points, right? So yes, absolutely, they're saying these are things
that happen. They're not saying these art things that happened or these things might not have happened.
.
These are things that happen.
But they're not doing what a modern historian does,
or claims to be doing, or tries to do when he writes history
and that they're not claiming to give an objective account.
Some kind of objective account that's accessible to anyone.
And so the equivalent of the Ken Ham on this side,
I'll go ahead and mention a couple of days.
When I was a kid, it was Josh McDowell with evidence
that demands a verdict, Mike Lekona does this now,
where they're trying to do modern history
and act like they can construct a modern historical argument
that will prove that Jesus rose from the dead.
Yeah.
I think that's a dead end.
I think the problem for us is modern.
people is we're so used to thinking in those terms that proving those claims equals this is true.
Right? That that's what truth is. But that's not the way that the Bible presents those things.
It's not in those terms. That's not these sort of forensic kinds of terms.
So there's multiple ways of seeing that something is true and making a...
Historical or scientific claim is not the only way to say that.
That makes sense.
For us today, for us today is modern people who have embraced modernism and had it drilled
into us if we haven't embraced it.
We think for something to be true, it has to be scientifically provable or there has to
be this overwhelming historical evidence or what have you.
What do you have shown?
Yeah, and so...
you know, and your village atheist because he's peak modernist will come and and
throw that stuff at you, right? And with history it's especially silly, right?
Because they'll come and say whatever it is you have that Jesus even existed and you go whatever it is you have that Alexander the great you've
existed. Yep, yep. Right, whatever it's you have that, you know, and Julia sees her ever.
existed. What? Because history doesn't work that way. Starting in the 18th and 19th centuries,
northern Europeans decided they wanted history to work that way. And they invented the social
sciences to try to make them work that way, right? Like sociology and anthropology and stuff to make
them sciences. But they don't work that way. So when I said that the Bible isn't making historical
claims I didn't mean that the Bible isn't saying that
those things really happen. The Bible is saying that those things really happen. But they're not
writing modern history. They're not trying to present you evidence, right, of
to prove to you that this is a thing that really happened. And approaching them that way,
trying to go to an APS to try to use the gospel accounts, like some of our evangelical friends do
with the best intentions that just they become modernists themselves in trying to prove
to other modernists that Christianity is true.
And it just, it doesn't work.
Because the way you frame your inquiry
will frame the results you get.
And so if you approach things
from the perspective of scientific materialism,
you're not gonna find anything spiritual
by using that method.
You're just, you're gonna get scientific materialist conclusions.
Yeah, so it sounds like
what you're saying if I'm hearing you correctly
is that their presuppositions are going to determine
that's gonna be a lens to which they view everything.
So I actually have a copy of evidence
at the massive verdict sitting like three feet away.
Yeah.
I once, I once, this is a true story.
This is a true story.
See, I grew up in Southern California.
I grew up right next to the headquarters
of campus crusade.
So I was at the epicenter of this stuff.
And I once argued with Josh McValod in person
God.
to admit that the stuff in that book is not evidence and it does not demand a burden.
Wow. So I was pugnacious as a child.
What is that helpful to you, Michael?
Yeah, I just have one small thing. There's a chart in that book which I'm sure you know about.
It measured the number of manuscripts.
And he says there's.
He compares the amount of manuscripts for the New Testament with manuscripts for other historical documents like
Seeders, Gollig Wars and all that, and he says there's 24,633 manuscripts for this, which means it's the most credible document of antiquity.
But it sounds like what you're saying is even if you use that argument on some kind of humian or something, you're going to be like,
Why just don't believe in miracles and resurrection?
So I don't care about how many manuscripts you have. Is that kind of what you're saying?
Yeah, that's gonna be humans response but also...
So, right, that just proves it's the most popular.
Yeah, I mean, it doesn't mean that what's in it is true.
It just means that lots of people copied it.
But it does-
The very striker show got the highest ratings
on television for a long time.
That is a media contained any great truth.
I mean, the usefulness of that data
is the ridiculous thing that some people say,
well, you know, it's been translated and copied
so many times we have no idea, you know,
what any of it really...
really was. Well, that's just not that's just someone who's never even looked at the data.
Right. So that's that is that is a good point. So that data is useful. And in fact,
I may have a book coming out soon that uses some data like that, but but that it's to make that
point. It's to make the point that actually we have a much better idea of what the original text
said that we do with any of those other books. Right. But that's different than saying that affects
the truth claim.
right? Yeah. You could, because you could say no, this is exactly what St. Mark wrote. I just
still don't believe it, right? You know, I think he was wrong. But yeah, yeah. And so,
friend of the show, Bart Irman, he's coming up a lot tonight. But yeah, he will say that. He will
act like we have no idea what the gospel's originally said or who wrote them. You know, it was
like what 30 years before they were
written down. I mean, nobody
remembers what happened.
30 years ago. So yeah, that's good in countering that. Right. But you're not really making a modernist
counter arm. You're just addressing him and saying like, what? You know.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling Michael and we're happy to hear that the show has
been helpful for you. Okay. We have one more caller that we're going to take and then we're going to
move on, so Samuel from Virginia.
I think is a multi-time caller, Samuel.
Welcome to Lord of Spirits, Christ is risen.
And he is risen, Father,
and I have a question about that.
All right, good.
Welcome back.
Yeah, so in some of the earlier episodes,
who was mentioned that ancient Mary Eastern cultures
thought of the realm of death as the bottom of the sea.
So, would there be any connection between...
walking on water and a trampling death underfoot?
What do you think, Father?
Sort of. There are, you've got to read the particular accounts. So, St. Mark's account is actually
there are deliberate verbal parallels to the Greek translation of Joe. So he's actually parallel
Chris walking on the water with the
particular passage in Job in order to identify Christ as the God of Israel.
But in St. Matthew's Gospel and St. Luke's Gospel, there's more clear illusion to sort of
bail language, bail being a storm god.
And there's even some bail Zeus stuff going on in the story of St. Paul Shipwreck in Acts.
that's a little further.
But yeah, so in so far as there is sort of a catholic bail, you can kind of get there.
But the focus is less on the trampling and more on Christ's power, super seating that of the storm and of the sea.
Right. Does that make sense?
Same you're fine.
but not quite.
That makes sense, thank you.
Alrighty, well thank you very much for calling
and we're going to roll on now with our conversation
about what happens when people die.
So the next part, the second half,
we've titled Paradise, Hades, and You.
Yeah, and hopefully the middle term will drop out of that.
Um, it's made for-
But yes, yes.
So where we ended up in the first half was that we're now in this Messianic age.
Right. And so usually when we talk about the Messianic age, we talk about the prison age, we're talking about our life in this world, right, in the church, right, Christ ruling in the midst of his enemies.
the flip side of that in the spiritual realm is
is what is called the intermediate state, usually by theological types.
And it's called the intermediate state because it's not the final or ultimate state, right?
It's isn't even anybody's final form, but it's this in between period, right?
As Michael number one said, it is comment on that prayer that souls translate to that place
were at a weight, right? That a weight.
is what we're talking about, right?
And so we're talking about the souls,
what happens to the souls of those who die in this life
during the Messianic age.
So before we were talking about what happened before, Christ,
right, now we're talking about during our current age.
And so we have these two terms that are used.
one is paradise and that of course paradise is the lone word in the Greek of
Genesis from Persian that I know I know just the Persians work around
when Moses was people are gonna get that again. Wait what?
Anyway.
the, the, the, isn't there guns and roses reference week be making here or no sorry.
I know the grass is probably green.
I don't know if the girls are pretty because there's supposed to be any of that in paradise.
That's true.
So, but so it's important that the word that's used for this place or state of being we're going to get into more about how we should understand that.
the fact that it's paradise, the fact that it's this name for e
for the garden is important, right?
Because as we've talked about in past episodes,
that entails a lot, right?
This is this walled garden, top the mountain of God.
This is the place where God dwells.
This is where his tabernacle, his tent is, right?
And we talked about the rooms and the tent,
paradoxes where the tree of life is, right?
That first resurrection language
that we were just talking.
about. And so all of that is brought along to communicate to us the status of the righteous
or the faithful who are departed this life, who have left this life in this world.
Yeah, so there's this not exactly identification but association with Eden for those, for the
the righteous who've left this world.
I mean, it's not, the word is used, paradise, but it's not.
understood to be exactly Eden. Well as we've talked about paradise is wherever God is. Yeah right.
Right. Right where God is that becomes the mountain of God that becomes paradise whether that's
right. The womb of the Theotokos whether that's Mount Sinai. So it is is about. And then right. Right. It is
being Eden and as we've talked about before when we're celebrating the Divine Liturgy the Church is
Yeah, well you know, it's actually the sexroom
It reminds me, a few years ago, I had the opportunity to go on a pilgrimage to Manatos.
And then when we left Manatos, we went to a women's monastery at a place called Ormelia.
And there was an elderly hire monk there named Father Siddapion who was from Semino Petromonasterian.
And he said something, and I love this.
He said something. I will always remember. He's since has died of cancer, actually, if I remember correctly.
But he said, if you live in repentance,
then the...
Kingdom of Heaven has already come.
And I love that as a summary of this, right?
That the Kingdom of Heaven is present where people are living in repentance.
So even then, yeah, it's just, I don't know.
I'm not going to say I think that should be a t-shirt, but at least it should be a cross
stitch or something.
I don't know.
It's really an amazing saying.
Something tasteful.
We're ready.
tasteful please. I can I can hear Father a step on in my head complaining about what he calls
Patrista memes but but but but there you are. But this is also say John Prasostum talks about this
right he says when when worship is happening that's where Christ is and where Christ is there are all
all the angels, they're all the saints, they're all the departed, right? So every time we get
gathering not just with the people, right?
That's why I sense the whole church during
that and see, even though there's only like two people there
and they're sitting in the opposite corners of the back,
right?
Because I'm not just sensing the people you can see, right?
Right.
The church is always full, right?
But also, even though I guess it's a tradition that's
gone a long time, I really want to attack the tradition
in certain parts of the Orthodox Church where when a love
one dies, people stay home from church for a while to mourn. That makes like zero sense to me.
Right. The person you're mourning is there in the church. Yeah. Why would you not want to be
present with them and with Christ? Yeah, and it's weird because usually they go everywhere else.
Put one at the church. Yeah. Anyway. Yeah. So that point's taken. You know, not a fan of that tradition.
Right. But then
So the flip side, unfortunately, is that there is this sort of remaining Hades.
Right?
But Hades is not to be confused, and there's some great coder language in our notes here.
But not to be confused with that final condemnation after the end of days.
Right?
It's not Tardarus, it's not the Abyss.
Right, this is not the place where the demons are.
are in prison, right?
Right.
This is Hades.
This is by the 4K of analogy.
This is where they ignorant and the wicked would go, right?
But they're not considered in the same way, right?
Right, right.
This is where some of these ideas start
to merge in people's heads where we've got that,
you know, the model that we said at the beginning
was basically garbage.
you know, if you go to heaven or hell when you die, you know, like I know, you know, you can sometimes
your fundamentalist preachers say things like and he's burning in hell right now. And by that,
what that what's happened is they've conflated what you just said, hedees this place of the wicked
and the ignorant for the time being with that final condemnation with images of the lake of fire,
you know, all this kind of stuff, but it's not, it's not the same
whatever word you use, it's not the same thing.
Right, you know, and then-
It's also a bit kind of a judgmental jerk.
Yeah, right.
But, you know, yeah.
Yes.
Also confusing these two.
Yeah.
Right.
And so, you know, even when we say there's some kind of distinction,
and hate these as experience.
experience, I guess, or paradise as experience between each other and even within Hades, maybe
that there's some kind of distinctions in that experience.
People kind of want to get that nailed down.
Well, wait, what do you mean?
Right?
Well, how is it not as bad?
How is it worse or what do you mean experience or what's it like?
Even our friend Michael number one.
He didn't give his last day so I don't want to say that.
out. But Michael, never want to ask about how time, right? How do you experience time in
that state? Right? And the ultimate answer is that we don't know. And it's not just that
we don't know. It's that we can't know. Right? Right? It's not possible for us to understand.
That's why we get these images and ideas and impressions from the scripture. Because
that's the most we can understand about it. Right? Because you don't know what it's like
to be a bad...
definitely don't know what it's like to be a dead bat, right?
And you don't know what it's like to be a dead human.
We don't know what it's like to not have a material body.
Yeah.
Because we've always had one.
And so all of these metaphors we have of both, right,
are material metaphors because those are things we understand, right?
Like a tent, right?
or...
or a garden or a mountain or fire or darkness or whatever metaphor you want to use, right?
These are all physical metaphors because that's how we our senses, right?
So we got our news. That's how we approach reality, right? So we can't know exactly what it's
that's gonna be like.
And even if somebody, you know, a saint
who has experienced physical death.
that comes back, you or she can't explain it to us
because again, we, until we also experience it, right?
It would be like, you know, a saint trying to explain to me
what it's like to be a departed saint
would be like me trying to explain to my dog,
Shelby what it's like to be a human.
Right, I mean, on some level,
it's the Plato's cave problem, right?
Where you've got the person who goes out of the sunlight
and tries to come back and tell the people
we've never seen something.
what that's about. But much more so because it's not just a matter of what someone has experienced.
It's a matter of being a different kind of someone. Right.
And having a whole different kind of experience. Yeah.
Right. Yeah.
Yeah. Senses that you don't have now. I mean, it's just we don't even, you know, like this is the
the man to strip thing again.
Right, right.
So we have to become
enough to accept our limitations as finite beings of a certain type.
Right? Yeah. But that doesn't mean there's nothing here now to be said. Right?
And we want to briefly kind of talk about there is a strong and good tradition in the Orthodox
Church that connects a period of 40 days after a person experiences physical death
before their soul
departs in another sense, right, to this state of paradise or
Hades, and even as I say that, it raises a thousand questions of, what do you mean
departs in a different sense? That what do you, why 40, etc, etc., right? So we have
to kind of address sort of what we mean when we even say, for example, what do we
mean when we say that person is still.
present in some sets with their loved ones for 40 days. What is present me? Because the way
we normally use the word present, right, is means that something occupies some quantity
of physical space, in proximity to the physical space that I am occupying. Right. That body
is near my body, such that I can sense it with my physical sense. Yeah. So that person
but it's present.
my mug of coffee is present in front of me on the desk.
The desk is present in front of me in the room.
Right?
I am present in this room.
Which if that's the only way that that can mean anything,
when Jesus says I'm with you always,
even to the end of the age,
people have to go really?
Because there's not a,
I don't see him standing here in the room with me.
There's not that kind of presence.
So it's a nervous.
Very good.
standing in the room. Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, which doesn't make sense. But so there's another way we talk about presence though. But the way to get to it is we have to actually kind of come out at backwards because the opposite of presence is absence.
Right, right.
And it's pretty clear that absence only exists phenomenologically, meaning absence.
since only exists as an experience.
Like I can make a mathematical argument
that two objects are near each other.
Right, I can give you a mathematical measurement
of the space and everything, right?
But there is no way mathematically or scientifically
to quantify all of the many millions of things
that are not in this room with me.
Right.
And I don't-
have any experience of most of them.
Like I don't walk into the room and be like,
aha, there is no hippopotamus here.
Right.
Like I don't experience the absence of hippopotamai
in my day to day life.
Right.
There is an absence of hippopotamai in my day to day life,
but I don't experience, right?
When we experience absence,
when we experience that something is gone
or something or someone is absent,
what we're experiencing is the fact
that we...
believe there is a place where that person or thing is supposed to be and that
person or thing is not there. Yeah it's it's you notice them missing you
miss that. I reach for my pocket the keys aren't there
hypetic briefly I realize they're in my other hand right but that's the
absence they're supposed to be there that's the place they're supposed to be and
and they're not there. Right? So.
When we talk about a person who has departed this life, the experience of absence is they're supposed to be here with me and they're not.
Right.
I'm supposed to be able to pick up the phone and call them and I can't.
Right. I want to talk to them and I can't and that's not right.
Right. So that's absence. So that presence to get to what presence means in the sense we have to then flip to the opposite of that.
Right? That we're talking about an experience that we have.
Right? An experience we have that mitigates against that absence.
That we don't, that there's this 40-day period during which we don't experience
that absence in the same acute way.
Right? And so this is notice that we're talking
here.
I'm not contradicting what I just said about us not being able to understand.
We're talking, when we talk about this tradition, from our perspective as the people who are
still living in this world.
Right, it's, you know, as you say, phenomenal logical, which is that is, this is our experience
of this, which is subjective.
It doesn't mean it's not real, but it is subjective.
It's our experience.
So our experience of the departed person, we're not making a claim.
about what the departed person is experiencing.
Because we don't have that perspective.
Because we don't know,
or where the departed person is, for example,
in terms of occupying physical space.
Right, I mean, and as modern people,
we tended to fault trying to think in those terms,
but we don't actually have access to that.
We don't have a detached access to what's going on out there.
We only have what we have.
Yeah, so the 40 days and the memorials and the traditions that are prescribed during that 40 days,
for that 40 day period are primarily for us. That is not to say that the memorials don't do
any good for the departed person they do, right? But specifically the 40 day period, particularly,
you know, we do memorials on this day and then that day, right?
Yeah, it goes for us.
Right, it's not that some spiritual scientist
has tracked the movements of a soul for 40 days
and figured out that they were wondering for 40 days
and they were gone.
And that's why we do memorials.
That's not what's going on at all.
So when people say that the memorials are for us,
like that's true.
They are also for the departed person,
but not in the same way that they are for us.
Right.
because we...
We would say that our prayers for the departed benefit the departed regardless of on what day
and at what time, right?
Right.
Tontics we say them, right?
But so the way of structuring our mourning and our memorials and our prayers for that, the
structuring is for us, right?
Right.
For the way that we experience time and the way we experience absence and loss.
So the structure is for us.
The content is for us and for them.
Yeah, right.
But the structure is for us.
Right.
So that covered, now let's talk about what a soul is.
Let's move to easier topic.
I actually saw recently someone did a review
of my latest book in which they accuse me of,
and this is not in there,
but they accuse me of treating the soul
like it's a physical object.
I was like, that's the opposite of what I believe.
have to hurry.
How do I know, right?
Am I some kind of originist?
But I'm sure you thought it was spherical.
I saw that in Willy Wonka and the Chalka factory,
the spherical soul anyway.
It's the same way that, right,
we've seen this sort of conceptual drift
surrounding the word and hell
that we talked about at the beginning of the first half, right?
There's also been this kind of conception.
will drift about a soul. So for example, people will act like it's crazy talk if you say
that anything but a human has a soul. They will talk about humans having an immortal
soul and not realize that that's not Christian at all. They will, when we picture a soul, people
to a picture, like, of a picture.
someone sold, they kind of picture like a force goes from the end of return to the Jedi
before the blue ray.
Right.
Or get out.
Anyway.
Wow.
No love for hating Christians.
I don't, yeah, no, I don't believe in it at all.
Not even the little.
So yeah, they'll picture like a force.
the kind of translucent image of the person's body.
that's their soul. And that's pretty far afield from the way the word was used by pretty much everybody in the ancient world.
So, for example, right off the jump in Genesis 1 on the fourth day of creation, or on the fifth day of creation when God creates the fish of the sea and the birds of the air.
It literally says he creates all the souls that swim in the sea and all the souls that fly in the air.
And these weren't spheres whipping around through the water and the sky
These aren't humans even these are animals
Right, and so it's very clear all through the ancient world whether we're talking about
The way soul is used in Semitic languages and theories whether we're talking about even Greek philosophy
Possible exception Plato because he gets a little weird with the reincarnation and stuff
Um, um,
But not even so much with him.
Basically, a soul is what makes a living thing alive.
Yeah.
Right.
So Lord Neffesion, he literally means life.
Yeah, I mean, you may think about, even think about the English word animal.
I mean, it just comes from Anima which means soul in Latin.
Right.
And we say that an object is inanimate if it's not alive.
Inanimate literally means
unsolved. No soul. Yeah. I mean I should play the
the etymology jingle. Oh wow. Yeah. And technically animation means you're
en souling drums. Oh man. So it's probably a kind of idolatry.
Dun dun dun dun. If you're looking for another reason to condemn Disney
everybody there you go. There you go. So whoo. So at this
for second carries onto the church box.
Right, you can look up saying Gregory Polymos talking about how animals have souls, right?
Now there are different types of souls.
Right. They're not saying everything has a human soul.
Right.
Right. They're saying they're saying that they have souls, but they're souls of a different type, right, than a human soul.
So you have sort of with plants which are alive and animals, you have what you might call micro souls.
Right?
or the way Aristotle works it out is you have sort of the most basic level of a soul, the
vegetative part, which is what plants have, where they take in nutrients and they grow and
they reproduce. Right? And that's sort of basic. Right? All living things have that basic level,
plants only have that basic work, right?
Then animals have the addition of desires.
that academia, which we usually translate as passions,
but animals have desires, right?
They get hungry, they get thirsty,
they need to sleep, they move about, right?
They seek to fulfill those desires, right?
And so that's, again, animals and humans both have that,
right, but animals sort of only have that, right?
And then humans have a noetic soul.
Humans have a new-
right? That gets translated through Latin and English as man being the rational animal,
but that kind of misses the point. It's, man has had noetic, right? Man has a news, right? And
that makes a human soul different than a point soul or an animal soul. So humans, if we take human
in souls of the baseline. Other living things have sort of micro souls. But.
then there's also, and this is a concept that we've mostly lost in the modern world,
although some folks are coming back to it, even atheists, is the idea of what we might
call macro-souls.
Yeah, right, which is this idea that larger systems, like whole communities of people, for
For instance, have a soul together, like the soul of a life.
Yeah, right.
There's this common life.
That is greater than the sum of the parts
And I think I think the reason why that this is a hard concept to grasp is because
We tend to want to think of the soul as being an object
Right rather than the life that exists within a
Person or a system or whatever, you know
But but it's true. I mean you think about like if you know if you've ever moved from one place to another
the new place has a
different way of being and you can just feel it and experience it and you
participate in it. You participate in the way of being of that place. And it's
something that's larger than just simply lining everybody up and just
watching what they do. Right. And it could be functional or dysfunctional.
It could be sinful. Yeah. Or it could be holy. Right. Which is why like
whole nations get condemned in scripture, for instance. Right. You know,
the bright, but even down to your parish community.
Not your church, right?
The way sin in the community is talked about in the New Testament, right?
Doesn't make sense if you're just thinking about it as a group of individuals who gather
together with a common purpose, right?
In which the individual sin of another person has nothing to do with.
Right.
Right?
So yeah, so a good way to think about it is to think about the fact that
in a human, right? In our human body, not only do we have completely unrelated organisms
living like our gut biome, but we don't even have to go there. Every cell in our body is a living
thing. It's a living organism, right? The cell is alive, right? While it's connected to our body at
least. They will die and get shed off, but it's alive. But yet, it makes up a greater whole.
Right. And so this also happens and this this is when St. Paul talks about the church community being the body of Christ.
And us being the members, the parts of the body and each of us playing this role so the whole body can thrive and function in Christ's head.
head and the body is animated by the Holy Spirit which is the spirit of Christ, right?
Made alive by it, right?
This isn't just...
sort of pure woo-woo metaphor again. He's pointing to something real, right? And St. John
can write his letters to the seven churches and talk about the church like it's an entity.
It has this one guardian angel, right? And he can say you have forgotten your first love.
Right.
And yeah, modern Western individualism makes this brain
breakingly hard for us to understand.
Yeah, we try to come up with other words like vibe.
Right? I mean, that's right.
It isn't in that in a template.
Like you're like, that group has a particular vibe,
which is simply, I mean, it's not the word that I would prefer.
It's not a theological word, but it's pointing at this reality.
we have a sense.
Often this is apparent, I think, when people go into a large crowd experience or sometimes
a very intimate experience with a particular group of people, and they'll say there was
a spirit there or a room had a certain feeling, that's what's being pointed to.
This is an experience we've all had over and over again.
But if you try to talk about it in some specific...
objective way, there's kind of, there's not much to point to there. I mean, someone might
talk about, I don't know, maybe Pharmaons or something, but I mean, there's, but there's
not a lot to kind of point at in any sort of empirical way, but nonetheless, it's an experience
that we've all had. And it's, it simply is part of what it means to be human.
Right. And this is, you know, way back when we were talking about sacrifice in the ancient
world. Right? The reason.
And there are spirits.
This is how powers and principalities work.
These are macro souls.
These are steps above us.
Let's say the animals of plants are steps below us.
That these complex systems in nature, in the heavens, et
cetera, that these are being super-intended by these spirits,
by these noetic beings, by angels.
and some of the...
them, some of them turn to evil, right? This is sort of how that works, right? But we're
so individualized and alienated now that everything below us, animals, plants, whatever, right?
The Earth itself, right? Nobody believe in a world soul anymore, right? The Earth itself
It's just, it's below us so it's not life in the sense that means anything.
Right?
only our human rational life means anything.
Everything below us is just resources to be exploited
and dealt with as they be.
And we believe that nothing above us exists, frankly.
Right, so all you have left are individuals.
And that's why nothing above us can exist.
Because we can't think of ourselves as I'm a cell
in a bigger organism.
I'm a part, playing a part in a larger body.
I'm the big toe, right?
larger body, right? I am, I am part of a larger whole and I am a subset of something.
We can't even think about ourselves. I am the unit. I am the individual. I am the one.
Anything below me is less than one and so unimportant and there's nothing more than one.
When we gather together, it's one plus one plus one plus one plus one plus one plus one,
right? We don't gather together and become one. And so, yeah, it's made it even hard for us
to think about it.
But if we're going to talk about souls and the episode, we're talking about life, right?
And so human life is one type of life, but there are levels of life below that and there
are levels of life above that within the creation, before we even get near to God, right?
Just within the creation.
There's a button above and below.
And so to come back around to where we started this half, the second half.
What we're talking about, what we're talking about the intermediate state is that the life
we live in the body, the life we live in this world, right, continues after it is separated
from our physical body.
you see someone who is alive and then you see them die afterwards.
has changed. The body is still there, but the life has left. That life does not cease to exist,
but that life becomes hidden from us. This is the language that the New Testament uses
there. Life is hidden in Christ. And so when we talk about this period and then the last judgment,
This isn't we're in a holding cell and then we're going to stand in front of the judge and
get condemned or get found innocent.
Right.
But it's actually that we are, our life is hidden, but continues until that day when Christ
comes to set everything in the creation right.
But what that means is that this intermediate state for us, whether we want to label it as
paradise or Hades and whenever gradations we want to talk about.
It's a continuation of the life we live in the body.
Yeah, we shouldn't think of it as,
like I don't think we mentioned this,
but there's these experiments, or maybe you did,
that we're done where the people try to figure out the weight
of a soul by measuring someone's weight.
Right. At the moment, they die, right?
That's not what's going on here.
The soul is not a thing that leaves the body
and goes somewhere up in the air or down below or whatever.
It's that the life of the body separates from it, but again, like we talked about presence,
what exactly does that mean?
The notion of it going down makes sense because when you put a human body into the ground,
there's this idea that the life of the body sort of dissolves into the ground.
But that we're not saying that that means that human souls are underneath Earth's crusts.
somewhere, right? It's that this is the image that we've got. You know, um, likewise the notion of
the soul going up is not that we're saying that they float up into the atmosphere. It's that
because we have this image of Christ as being ascended and the life has hidden in Christ,
that idea of, of up makes some sense. But we're not talking, we're not saying that it's a location
because when Christ ascended he didn't...
fly up into the atmosphere and land somewhere in space.
That's not what's going on.
So again, when we talk about up and down and all that kind of stuff,
it's sort of spiritual geography in a sense, right?
It's not a spot, right?
Right, right.
Yeah, right. And so the key is that there's that there's that continuity.
Right, so if we've lived our life in the body following Christ, trying close to Christ, coming to know God in Christ, then that continues.
That life continues after the separated from our body.
The flip side is if we've lived our life in rebellion against God and hatred against God,
Right, in rejecting him, then that life also continues.
Right, when we leave the body.
But ultimately, we're waiting...
for that day to come, that last day when Christ will restore perfect justice.
Which we'll talk about more in the future.
Exactly.
In the meantime, we pray because that day has not come yet because that day has not come yet.
But we pray for our departed.
We pray for each other in preparation for that day.
Okay, we're going to go ahead and take our second and final break and we will be right
back.
of other interesting-
David and David and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity?
that you can't trust strangers in internet forums to answer.
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking for a reliable first place
to send your interested friends?
Do you need help finding an Orthodox Church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodge.
I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North America.
My name is Father Joseph Lucas.
I serve in the Orthodox Church in America.
My name is Father Anthony Cook.
I serve in the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick, Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith Ministries,
and a priest of the Antioch Narcissist.
And where the Orthodox Intro Team.
If you're looking for a first stop online to get an introduction to the Orthodox Faith,
a place to get answers to questions from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy, a place
to send your friends and not just toss them into the chaos of the Internet, a place to get
help finding an orthodox parish and get plugged into an actual orthodox
community, then point your web browser at orthroxintro.org.
Orthroxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith
ministries and made possible by our donors.
It's an orthrox enramp to the Christian life.
Again, that's orthroxintro.org.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Look back, it's the third half.
It's the third half.
We're talking about what happens when people die.
So, first part.
Oh, go ahead, good.
If I could give you one note on the Orthodox intro.
Oh, sure, yeah.
I'm not going to edit it now but okay.
Well, what would have raised it to the level of perfection, right?
It would be if during your bit after you introduced yourself, you did the, and we are dramatic
pause.
And then everyone says in unison, the Orthodox infrotein.
That would be pretty, yeah, yeah, no, I mean, I hear you.
Next level.
But it's a level of like I wasn't going for cheesy.
I was cheesy was not where I was aiming with that with that
and you say cheesy I say engaging
go planet anyway
That's actually almost a little too young for me.
Captain planet was was not from my youth.
That was from a little bit young for well, you and I are about
same age. I think it was a little bit
I think we might have been teenagers or when that came out.
I have to go. Despite the peak 80s mullet, that is true.
Right. Right. Exactly. So, all right. Well, it is the third half.
And now we're, I mean, we're actually following a fairly clear structure.
So the first one we were talking about, you know, the underworld prior to the coming
of Christ in the second part, now death, what happens at death during this
messianic age. And now we're talking about the life of the world to come.
So this is what's in the future from our point of view.
So sometimes what I do make sense.
It's not what I'm talking about.
So coming back to where we began, this idea that probably most, at least American Christians
having their head.
That, well, you know, you live in this world and you die.
And if you're a good Christian, you're going to have them.
And if not, you're going to hell.
Yeah.
And both of those last forever, that is a sub-Christian eschatology.
That's not Christian.
Right.
Actually, that's Nostek.
Dun dun dun.
Yeah.
So just about everybody's a Nostek.
Don't be Nostek, everybody.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
So yeah, and that's bad.
Yeah.
So there was a book that Harold Bloom wrote a long time ago now, because I'm old.
A long time ago now called the American Religion.
It was sort of a religious history of the United States.
was an abound, I think, that...
Yeah, yeah.
But he's a Yale Shakespeare professor and then about
DOSIC himself, but he did sort of our
religious history of the United States and argued
that American Christianity with a couple of
of exceptions that he outlines was pretty much all
not.
And this was one piece of that that there wasn't really
a firm belief in a bodily resurrection.
And that the there was going to be a new heavens and a new
Earth that we're going to live in.
on the earth and resurrected bodies, right? That was not a firm reality in most people's heads.
And then also the way just in general American Christianity of all stripes, so this comes out of
sort of the Puritan base, was very world denying and very sort of anti-material enjoyment and pleasure
and just the idea of worldlyness meant sin, right? So it was like even things that you can't make a
good biblical case.
like playing cards, you know?
We're seeing as just kind of tainted
because there were things of the world.
Yeah.
Right.
And that sort of,
the stain for the material world,
it's kind of
innately not stick.
And I just, I just, I just looked it up
and that book came out in 1992.
It has been a long time.
Yeah.
Man.
I was young once.
My heart was an open book.
Thank you.
I was young and foolish then, I feel old and foolish now.
So, one of the sneaky ways that
NOSIS system falls into our Christianity, like chocolate and
or peanut butter, is except that makes it better.
NOSIS system makes Christianity.
I'm on the table.
Yeah, okay, okay.
adverse recent situation. So is through Platinum.
Okay. We often forget if we ever knew that Plato's Tamaez was part of the Nagamadi library,
the fine in 1948 about the Nostic texts, included Plato's Tamaez, Plato's account of the creation of the world.
And...
Well, there have been especially in the West a lot of attempts to fuse play this in Christianity.
Bad news for you, they don't really dovetail.
Because there are basic ontological meaning related to being.
what is and what isn't.
Presuppositions that play do has that don't really work with.
Chris.
And so you end up getting something closer to anostasis.
One of the places where the surface is,
it's your main to our topic tonight,
is the whole idea of the beatific vision in the world.
Oh, man, big throwdown now.
Yeah, I'll deal with it.
The whole idea of the beatific vision,
the idea that the soul, once it is freed from the body,
Once it is freed from the body.
could be hold the essence of God,
could be hold the divine essence,
and that is its state for eternity.
Even as I said that, you probably noticed a bunch of problems.
So first of all, the soul being freed from the body,
whereas with the scripture's teach or Christianity teaches
is that the soul separating from the body is unnatural.
That is bad.
And that our destiny is to be rejoined.
to our body, right?
Excerprate from the body is not good or better, right?
Number two, the idea that the soul can
then behold divine essence.
They come to know the essence of God.
Yeah, no thing.
And be conformed to it by that seeing.
And then third, if that's the eternal state of the soul,
what happens to the body?
bodily resurrection.
Right.
And so Western theology in particular passes through this plate this period.
From Augustine through, you know, BTS into the, into the beginning, through late antiquity
and into the early medieval period.
And folks who come along try to reckon with this problem.
Right.
Thomas Aquinas tries to kind of deal with the...
issue, right? And in the third part of his summa. Now, Thomas didn't finish the summa. He
had a mystical experience that caused him to think it was garbage, right? That's why he didn't
want to finish it. So the third part was compiled from his notes. So it may be that Thomas had some
solution to this problem. But if he did, we'll never know what it was.
do find in his notes is that he affirms this whole beatific vision idea. The soul free from the body
can be hold the divine essence, but then also affirms the bodily resurrection. Yeah, because he
is a Christian, right? So he's got to affirm that. So, but there's no conceivable way that those
to dovetail based on what's on paper now. So like I said, you might have had...
something in mind that we'll never know to try and reconcile those two but it's
not there. Yeah it's not there. And so one of the pieces that's problematic about
this they say you know thinking you can behold the divine essence is enough but
the idea that you're then conform to it right is picking up on this basic idea in
in Plato that multiplicity is bad.
That the good and the true and the beautiful and the perfect have to all be one and simple.
Right.
And I think that this has written deep into our culture.
Like if we see things that are multiple or complicated or there's lots of different ways
we tend to say, why can't this just be one?
We just need one way.
You know, one, I mean, and at its worst, right?
This becomes totalitarianism, the way that it gets played out.
Right.
People say it all the time.
They say, hey, we may all be wrong, but we can't all be right.
Only one of us could be right.
Right.
That's the, yeah, exactly.
And I mean, and this is the basis, for instance, I got to ask the other day when I pointed
out, you know, within the Orthodox Church, for instance, there are multiple canons of
Scripture.
I mean, they're mostly the same, but there's, and what you get to the early time.
the old testament. Yeah, exactly. Yeah. And like, well, why hasn't that been worked out by now?
Like, because we've never seen it as a problem that has to be worked out. You know,
that there's it's, it's okay. Multiplicity is okay. Not all diversity equals contradiction.
And there's, there's all kinds of practical places where this place itself out in the rest,
to the west, like the west's seaming inability to regard-
marriage and monasticism or marriage and virginity as equal, as two equal paths to holiness and to God.
Right. Right. You have an emergent tradition in Rome of virginity being the higher way of life, right?
and then, but some people can't do it,
because they don't have the special graces to do it.
And so, they're allowed to get married
as a sort of concession.
And then,
people are allowed to be together as long as they're trying to produce a child.
Right?
Etc.
They can't be co-equal and then you get the Protestant Reformation which reacts in the
exact opposite direction.
Right.
Where anybody who would pursue celibacy is some kind of weirdo.
Right?
And marriage is it, everybody should be married.
Right.
you can't have as we have been in the east, these are two paths.
different kinds of people, right? There has to be a higher and a lower, there has to be a better and a worse,
and whatever is lower or worse has to in some sense be kind of simple, right?
And kind of bad. By virtue of not being the good and the good can always just be this one.
There's this one right answer, right? And what's the right way to do it? What's the right answer?
There can't be multiple ways. There can't be multiple ways to see this. There can't be multiple ways to approach this, right?
but everything.
from our Christian tradition tells us the opposite.
Right?
Yeah, we have thousands of saints all conform to the likeness of Christ, but who are all very
different people.
With different personalities, different genders, some of them are married, some of them are
monastics, some of them are clergy, some of them are laity, some of them are martyrs,
some of them died of old age, right?
Living in all different times and all different places and all different cultures, some of
of growth, some of them were illiterate.
Some of them were, were theologians.
Some of them were very simple people.
Some of them were hemnographers.
Some of them could carry a tune in a bucket, right?
And we see that and we don't like taxonomize them.
Right.
Like, well, we got the bail token up at the top
and then the next tier and then the next tier
and then each of these is a little worse, right?
So.
That's not the Christian tradition.
It's multiplicity is fine.
And the whole idea that simplicity is better than multiplicity.
That the number one is somehow superior and more noble and beautiful than the number two or three.
It's just a weird Pythagorean religious presupposition that Plato had.
There is no basis in reality for it.
Right. Right.
Yeah.
All right.
So.
We can just kind of jettison it, right?
Like we don't know, play it on anything.
Right.
Yeah, and if you look, and if you look at the scriptures, this isn't there, you know, and
I mean, this is also the base.
I mean, there's a number of ways this gets practically worked out.
I mean, you mentioned marriage and menaces, and for instance, but even, for instance, when
people say, well, the gospel should be simple.
Whenever you start talking any kind of level of theology or whatever, there's some people.
not everybody, not most people maybe, that will say things like, well, the gospel should be simple,
because they're used to a very simplified version. And so therefore, anything beyond that is a
complication that violates this principle of simplicity. Even though when the apostles
preach the gospel, it's not some two-sentence elevator speech. It never is. And even the short
versions are predicated upon O-
whole tradition usually that they share with the person
they're talking to.
Which often we don't share.
Let me be even more controversial.
Okay.
The solas of the reformation.
This alone, that alone, this alone, that alone.
Yeah. Why?
Why alone?
Why can't there be richness?
Yeah.
Right.
Like why?
Why is everything up to be one and simple and no
just this right and this is how it is.
Right, it's all these these platonic and let's not forget Plato not actually a Christian.
What?
Right, and so the other the other big piece of this is is the whole issue of matter, the body.
Right, that that somehow being in the body makes this all unable to see God.
No God to behold the button somehow being freed from it, you know the body being
the prison house of the soul according to Plato and John Calvin, that somehow that then
frees the soul to do this, so that matter, the material body, the material world, by virtual
being material is somehow a negative.
And this is sort of the gnostic starting point, and it comes from these platonic presuppositions
that as soon as a God emanates or creates something other than himself.
by virtue of it not being him since he is the good and it is not him it is therefore in some sense bad or evil
Right because the good can only be can only be one and that again is completely counter
The Christianity which teaches from literally the first page of the Bible
The God called everything he created good. Hmm. Yeah
And so for us.
as Christians matter is the vehicle for God's grace, for the divine energies, for God working
in us. Right? So our body is the vehicle through which our salvation has worked out.
It's not a detraction from coming to know God. It's the way in which we as created human finite
beings come to know God is through our bodies, including our material physical body.
Okay.
talked about body and the different senses, right? And this, of course, we're coming back
to the incarnation again, right? This is where we see that most fully, right? When God works
our salvation in Christ, right, He does it by taking Him upon Himself our human nature,
including our human body. Yeah. And He doesn't get rid of it. No.
at the resurrection.
Or at least...
because now he's free.
No, right. He's got a human body forever.
This is a permanent union.
Yes, yes.
Right. So, all that said.
All of this to say, that's problem.
What we are looking forward to is the transfiguration,
the transformation, the salvation of the world, the cosmos.
It's a Greek word, cosmos, that's translated as world.
So does it just
being earth, that means the universe, right? The whole creation, right? That's what we're
waiting for. We're waiting for the resurrection of the whole creation, right? Which, according
to St. Paul and Romans, groans awaiting. Right. And so when we talk about Christ and His
glorious appearing judging the world, we mean as we said before tonight, Him putting it all
back in order. The whole unit
gets put back in order.
It gets put back to what it was created to be, all functioning as a whole.
Right? And that includes all the creatures.
Creature means something created.
That includes humans. That includes things lower.
That includes things higher, the angelic beings.
And so, then creatures who refuse to be put back in order,
who refuse to be justified.
right? They're excluded from that order, which means they're excluded from creation.
They're excluded from the cosmos.
Yeah, which and once the world has been put back in order, we've talked about these two
functions. This is the new creation, right? So we talked about the two functions. There's
putting things in order and then the world is going to be transfigured, meaning it's going
to be filled with the life of God.
Yeah, which is just just essentially a repeat but but not just a repeat.
but a fulfillment of what was the pattern that was begun in Genesis, you know, with the
religious order created and then it's filled.
Right.
And so the whole cosmos is transfigured and filled with the life of God and the divine
energy that includes all creatures, creatures below us, the creatures above us.
Right.
And any creatures who refuse the life of God, who are subdued in the life of God are excluded
from the life of God.
They're excluded from it.
But this is what
I, I think I said it in a blog post once.
This is why you can say that the Holy Spirit
is the atmosphere of the world to come.
Hmm.
That's cool because it's a cool way to put it.
Divine energy permeate everything.
So what does that mean?
What does it mean for a creature,
whether it be a demonic power or a human,
to be excluded from the cosmos?
All right.
Okay.
excluded from creation, or to be excluded permanently from the life of God.
Right? Well, again, we're talking about a different age. We're talking about the life of the age to come.
We don't know, hopefully none of us, none of us, listen to us ever will know what that means exactly.
But, again, we're given sort of metaphors and images, right?
and impression by the Scripture to help us try to understand what that would mean.
Yeah.
And so we get the image of the lake of fire that first had that.
As I said, that's probably the one that most people think of immediately burning.
You know.
Yeah.
And that's that first appears in text that we still have in the book of e-next, but then gets picked up in Matthew and Revelation.
Now, and explicitly said that this is made for the devil and his angels.
Right, right. That's what's created for. It's not created for people, right?
But the people who choose to become like the devil and his angels end up there with them, at least potentially.
You get the image of outer darkness or just darkness in general, right?
We get these images of being shut outside, whether it's being shut outside, the wedding banquet, or shut outside the kingdom, right?
right there are gates or doors and they are outside.
What does it mean to be outside the gates of...
created reality. Again, we don't know exactly.
Yeah.
We get this image of madness, which is what weeping and gnashing of teeth is about.
That's not an image of pain. That's that you look at places where those
Greek words are used, like in classical literature. It's always just
describing someone who's gone mad. Right?
And sort of all of those can be sort of summed up as a kind of
the humanisation, the diminution.
of human nature becoming less human. Right. So it's less like Christ because Christ has is the
perfection of our human nature. Yeah. So the image that some people have where this experience
God forbid that any of us have it is us as we are now being inflicted with horrible pain and torture
forever ever is predicated upon a whole set of a
that simply are not there.
You know, the biggest one being that we will be essentially be as we are now.
Right, but it's not.
Again, you said there's this dehumanization, this subhumanization,
because that's what sin does to you.
You know, if Christ is the perfect man, then, as you said,
you know, it's hitting in the opposite direction.
Right, right.
Alright, and so...
Since we can't really understand what that is,
that we just get these images,
why are we given these images in these metaphors?
Like what function does that serve?
Yeah, right?
Because we add the call about the claim language, right?
Like since we're just given impressions and analogies,
the scriptures again can't be by making a claim.
Here is it precisely what is going to happen to people
who, right?
Who can't be saying that,
because we're not given that kind of detail, right?
So why are we given these impressions?
And so, don't understand that we have to look at how it functions
in the life of the Christian, because these images are given
to Christians.
All right, they're not aimed at the world.
Right, we don't see the apostles going into a pagan Greek city
and saying, all y'all are going to burn for eternity if you don't
get right.
Right?
And you know, it's not the gospel, as they
right? It's the exact opposite. Right? They come and tell them about Christ. Right?
What Christ has already done for them and now what you required them and they say,
what must I do to be seen? Right. And it's not used in Scripture or in the
fathers to threaten people outside the church. Right. This is a huge point. I can
her mother was out publicly many times.
For anyone to find me an example of a church father talking about Christians,
you like the ones he's talking to when he preaches, y'all are going to heaven, but then bad people out there,
they're all going to hell.
Yeah, and I know it's semi- maybe classes, I don't know, that I do the Southern draw whenever I talk to you talking to you.
Um, so
But they're about there. They're all going to hell because that's not what you ever see, right?
What you see is hell is for Christians. You see church fathers threatening the good church people who are showing up to hear them preach with hell.
And hell here being not a word for the underworld hell now referring to the state of eternal condomation.
of nation. Yeah, with the journal
condemnation with being shut out
of the kingdom without a
darkness with weeping.
actually of tea. If you look at where those images appear in Christ's parables, he's addressing
them to the people he's talking to. This is your potential fate.
Yeah, this is an important point. I mean, we've said several times, one of my favorite sayings,
you know, there's no tale without a teller, but there's also no tale without a hearer.
And the hearer is really important. Who is Christ talking to? I mean, you've made this point
in a number of times in your whole Council of God.
podcast, for instance, when St. Paul is talking to Piggins, he speaks in a certain way.
When he's talking to Jews, he speaks in another way. And that's very deliberate.
Right? That you can't isolate these things from that context and try to come up with some kind of
independent system. Right? So that's right.
You treat them as some kind of objective truth claim or a logical proposition that you can take
out of context and assess. Right. Right. Right. There's a point. There's a point to.
this being addressed to Christians, right? And we've got to actually have a couple of quotes
from some modern saints that address this. You know, as you said, this serves a function within
the human, the Christian life. So what is the function? Well, the function is for me to struggle to
repeat. Right so what does that look like? So this is that classic saying from
and see it's still on the air for now.
who had this, this is the most famous thing you ever said,
keep thy mind and hell and do not despair.
So he says, keep your mind and hell.
He's not saying,
Astridly, project your nuisance to the underworld.
Like that's not what he's saying.
He's talking about,
remember that this possibility exists
and yet do not despair.
others move forward and hope move forward and in
repentance and struggle, right? That the purpose of this image is to bring us to repentance. It's not to lay out
prophecies about the future or who's going to heaven and hell or that's not the point at all. Like there's there's that and then the other one
The other one
From a modern saint is from Saint Piusius the Athanite
Yeah, go ahead
that
to reiterate what you're saying, right?
So this serves a function, this is a possibility for me,
that I could suffer this, I could suffer eternal condemnation
and it's a possibility for the people who are within
my spirit of responsibility, the people who I have
spiritual care for.
The reason it's a possibility for them is because
I have spiritual responsibility for them.
And so I need to be aware that it's a possibility for me,
It's a possibility for the people in my-
parish who I pastor and therefore I have to keep that in mind as I pastor them and try
to leave them away from it as a possibility. It's a possibility for family members who
are under my authority, right? But it is not a possibility that I extend to, definitely
not a certainty to people I don't like, people outside of that sphere of responsibility,
Right, so it is always tied to this is the possibility if I
fail. Yeah, this is the
possibility. If I don't move up to my responsibilities, if I don't repent,
if I don't seek after Christ, if I don't pursue Christ, right? And so
it is not making any kind of objective claim to who, if anyone,
will end up suffering this fate. Right. Right. I mean, it could be
billions of people, or it could be zero. That's irrelevant. Yeah, we don't know.
Yeah.
We don't know and it's funny like well, I'll be back up a
Number of church fathers. I recall saying things like always apply everything to yourself
You know that and not others. Yeah, right unless you know and and
I only apply it to others if I am responsible for them because God gave me them like so a parent and their children
and a pasturnous flock, but in that case it's not applied to others like you.
as others. I've got here, I'm hurling this at you. You have to listen, you know, like that's not
the point. That's not the way authority works in Christ, right? But it's, it's, you know, you
always, I'm the chief of sinners. Like, do I actually believe that? Or can I at least function
like that? I mean, that's that's simply another way of saying what saints of the one said,
and keep your mind in hell and do not despair.
Yes, I am the chief of sinners.
That's the...
It's the same, it is functionally exactly the same thing.
And you know, so this is good.
Before you give that quote, I want to give that quote.
So the problem when people start debating universalism.
Right. And there are some folks who are some still identify as Orthodox Christians.
A couple now don't anymore, but who professes to be universalism.
the problem with the
All of those discussions is that if we really have the discussion, we're going to end up
talking past each other because universalism is arguing about how many people are going
to end up in eternal condemnation, which is again making a type of claim that's kind
of irrelevant to the Christian life.
And the people who tend to respond to universalists to say, no, lots and lots of people are going
it's a journal code of nation.
Or again, it's sort of like with the, with young earth creationism, right?
They're adopting the same presuppositions in order to respond.
Right.
So, how many people that ends up being, whether it's zero or billions or somewhere in between,
is irrelevant to the role which the possibility of eternal condemnation plays in our lives.
So even if universalism ends up being true, and wouldn't it be great if it didn't?
Even if it ends up being true, you can't be a universal.
Right, right.
That'd be a Christian.
Yeah.
So, okay, I've had fake it twice now.
That's great quote from Steve Piusi, he's the at the night.
He's saying essentially this.
He says, struggle with all your power to gain paradise.
And do not listen to those who say that everyone will be saved.
This is a trap of scene.
so that we won't struggle. In other words, he says that to say categorically all
will be saved is a trap of Satan so that we won't struggle. In other words, he
identifies very clearly what the position of that universalist claim is in
Christian life. It's so that you won't struggle. You know, and you don't see
doesn't say there, no, this isn't true.
Yeah, he's not claiming to know that.
He doesn't say that all will be saying.
Right.
He says, you can't listen to that because then you won't struggle and repent.
Because, you know, St. Piusius, he had a lot of spiritual gifts and one of his spiritual
gifts was spiritual direction, you know, to give help to souls, right?
in a very, very powerful, powerful way.
And this is what...
of the things that he said to somebody. So yeah, I mean, the only thing that like we can
really truly say that we know about eternal condemnations that the demons are going to experience it.
But as far as human beings are concerned, for me, it exists as a possibility because
it spurs me to repentance. I'm not saying it's the only thing that should spur me to repentance.
right there's so many good reasons to repent that
are not just about, I'm afraid of this, but it is there. And it's there for a purpose.
It's not there. And the purpose that it's there for is repentance. It's not there for us
to lay down condemnation on others or to set up some kind of system of people who are
going to heaven and hell. That kind of thing. So, all right, well, to wrap up, I had a couple
of thoughts and then of course, Father Stephen will say his thoughts and then it will be done.
So the first thing I just wanted to just wrap up this question of universalism, saying that
we can't preach it is not some kind of noble lie because that would be saying that we know
it's true, but we're going to pretend it's not so that people repent.
We don't know that it's, we don't know.
We simply do not know.
It is not written in the scripture that all will be saved no matter what.
So we cannot preach that.
So what?
Why do we have these things?
Why do we have not just this question about universalism, but all the rest of the stuff
we've talked about in this episode?
To me, it always comes back to what St. John writes in his Gospel in chapter 20.
He says, now Jesus did many other signs in the presence of the disciples which are not
written in this book, but these are written so that you may believe that Jesus is the
Christ, the Son of God, and that by believing you may have life in his name.
This is what when I was...
in seminary we use the fancy theological term the
soteriological motive.
This is the soteriological motive.
In other words, the point of all of this is so that we
can be saved, not so that we have knowledge about things.
It's so that we can be saved.
So then the question is how does what we've talked about
in this episode aim us towards that?
So understanding what used to happen when people died
before the hearing of Hades, what now happens
when they die during the messianic age and what will happen after the resurrection when no one will die anymore,
how does this inform, for me, one of the big questions always is how does this inform our evangelism?
Because evangelism is precisely the work of bringing the salvation to other people, which is what we're supposed to be doing.
So number one we talked about, you know, in the old covenant.
This is relevant because we understand.
stand the feet that Christ has saved us from.
Like we talked about what the underworld is like
and various different takes on that.
Christ has saved us from that.
And we enter into that through our baptism
and of course, especially the ritual participation in Posca.
Right?
So that's an element of the way that we preach the gospel.
Then second, you know, if we understand
what happens now we're in the Messianic age.
One of the things we see that is what...
the scenes are doing and why they're not come like some sort of bonus add on to Christianity.
Like it's rather a testament to the belief and the resurrection of the dead. They are a testament to
that. This is the resurrection that Abraham Isaac and Jacob and all the scenes are participating in.
This is why we call the Lord the God of the living. And also we understand if we understand this
this messy and it's age we understand why things are not perfect yet. And here's the
in part what we're supposed to be doing in the meantime.
Right.
And then finally thinking about that age to come,
we understand that the possibility exists.
Again, we don't know to what extent it'll be realized,
but the possibility exists for being outside the kingdom.
So we, because we have seen this and heard this,
we strive through repentance to be more and more conformed
to it in this life as a preparation for the life
that is to come.
So
So much of this is bound up in our hope of what it means to be in Christ.
And so I think if we have a clearer understanding of the soul after death, what that means
before Christ, now during the Messianic Age and then after the resurrection, this is very,
very relevant to our evangelism.
It's very, very relevant to our daily Christian life.
So this is really core catacetacles.
stuff everybody. Father Steven? So I want to also talk about and hopefully clarify a little
the the relationship of this possibility of eternal condemnation and repet because as
Father Andrew just said this isn't like a noble line we're not saying oh yeah really everybody say
but we got to tell people that so they were home.
Right?
And part...
of the reason that breaks apart is we're not really talking about fear. We're not
talking about the kernel condemnation is here this horrible punishment, right? God is threatening
us with this horrible punishment. So you better say you're sorry and you better get this
good grace as he's going to lower the boom on you when the last judgment comes. Because
if you're paying attention during the show, we're talking about that's not how it either
works right but we
We tend to think about repentance most of the time at a very shallow level, that level of
kind of, oh yeah, I was a jerk, I'm sorry.
Let's just forget about it now.
Maybe we go a little deeper, hopefully we go deeper than that.
And we start to get to, I need to do better, I need to be better, I need to work to do better
and to be better, I need to work to follow Christ, to change, to be more like him.
I need to be better.
at the roles that I play, the purpose I play in the bodies,
in these larger, these macro souls we talked about, right?
The part I play in my family
as a spouse, as potentially apparent,
my role in the church, my role for places I need
to do better at it.
But there's an even deeper level than that.
I don't claim to have plumbed the depths
repentance myself.
or even gotten near the deepest levels, but there is a deeper level at which
repentance really takes the form of self-knowledge, of knowing ourselves
specifically in terms of knowing the depths of what we're capable of, the depths
of the evil that we've let come to live within us. And one of those is
really understanding the reality that we could,
at any moment we chose, destroy everything.
Every one of us has the power
to wreak havoc and destroy our family,
to do damage and destroy our parishes,
to ruin our lives, to burn it all down.
It wouldn't even be difficult if we decided to do it.
That's always there.
Sometimes in our dark moments, we even feel tempted to maybe do it.
It's never really far from us. We like to pretend it is.
Because of course, we all think that, you know, faithing and pretending that we're good people
is the first step toward becoming good people and it's not the opposite.
And so part of keeping our mind in hell, part of remembering that eternal condemnation is a possibility.
He is remembered
how that eternal condom nation would come about.
Eternal condom nation is not a possibility for me because I might make some mistakes or mess up.
Oops.
Eternal condom nation is a possibility for me because it's within my power to be truly vile,
to be truly evil, to hurt people,
to mistreat people,
to do damage to people in the world, to be cruel,
It would be heartless.
That's why eternal condemnation is a possibility to me.
And if we're not aware that we have that capability and that capacity, then we can't every day
consciously reject it.
We can't every day look at those actions that would bring us to that condemnation, those
derisity demonic tendencies that we've allowed ourselves to become infected with through the
passion.
You can't look at them and ward them off and set them aside and say no to them because
we're not willing to acknowledge that they're there.
So I think having this idea of hell in English, get hang out, whatever we want to call it,
eternal condemnation, the lake of fire.
It's not important in terms of making us afraid or afraid of God or watch our
step, but it's important that we remember the way that we would get there and how close
at hand that is so that we can consciously say no.
Consciously rejected and choose Christ instead.
Consciously reject the hate that we have within us and choose love instead.
Consciously reject the anger within us and choose peace instead.
You can't have that.
consciously reject the greed, the lust within us, and choose faithfulness instead. That
I think is a deeper level of repentance that we need to work to achieve. And the reality
of the possibility of eternal condemnation is one of the best roads that can help get us
there. So those are my thoughts.
Amen well that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't get through to us live,
we'd still love to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritzidationFaith.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page
or you can leave us a voicemail at SpeakBip.com slash LordofSpiritz.
We're a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays
of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific
and use the code LordofSpiritzidrayChattel Legends
and might get you something, no problem.
And if you are on Facebook
you can like our page, join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
Word of mouth, everybody.
And finally, be sure to go to ancientpaste.com, stroke support, and help make sure we and
lots of other AFR podcasts stay on the air.
Try the code on HelloFresh, too.
What have you got to lose?
Thank you, good night.
God bless you.
Christ has risen.
He truly is risen.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the
beasts and the elders and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousand
of thousands, saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land that was slain to receive power,
and riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.